<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The discovery of the Popish Plot being the several examinations of Titus Oates, D.D., before the High Court of Parliament, the Lord Chief Justice, Sir  Edmund-Bury Godfry, and several other of His Majesty's justices of the peace.</title>
            <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41099</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13593879</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13593879</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100713</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100713)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 797:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The discovery of the Popish Plot being the several examinations of Titus Oates, D.D., before the High Court of Parliament, the Lord Chief Justice, Sir  Edmund-Bury Godfry, and several other of His Majesty's justices of the peace.</title>
                  <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</term>
               <term>Godfrey, Edmund Berry, --  Sir, 1621-1678.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100713:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100713:1"/>
            <p>THE DISCOVERY OF THE Popiſh Plot, BEING The ſeveral Examinations of TITUS OATES D. D.</p>
            <p>Before the High Court OF PARLIAMENT, The Lord CHIEF JUSTICE, Sir EDMUND-BURY GODFRY, And ſeveral other of His MAJESTY's JUSTICES of the PEACE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, 1679.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100713:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100713:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Titus Oates</hi> D. D. his Journal and Affidavit of his Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Conſpiracy, before Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury Godfry, Septemb.</hi> the 27th. 1678.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IMprimis, Richard Strange</hi> Provincial, <hi>John Keines, Bazil Longworth, John Fenwick,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hartcourt,</hi> Jeſuites, did Write a Treaſonable Letter to Father <hi>Sinman</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Jeſuite at <hi>Madrid,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Spain,</hi> in which was contained their Plotting and Contriving a Rebellion in <hi>Scotland,</hi> of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians againſt the Epiſcopal Government, in order to which, they have imployed one <hi>Matthew Wright, William Morgan,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ireland,</hi> to go and Preach under the Notion of Presbyterians, and give the diſaffected Scots a true underſtanding of their ſad States and Conditions which they were in, by reaſon of Epiſcopal Tyranny exerciſed againſt them; and withall to tell them, now they had a fair opportunity to Vindicate their Liberty and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and that it could be done by no other way but the Sword, and that now the King was addicted to his Pleaſure, that he would and could take but little care of that Concern. In the ſaid Letter it was expreſſed, they had gotten an Intereſt in His Royal Highneſs, but they deal with him as they think fit, and that they were reſolved by all means to weaken the King of <hi>England</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, by informing his Friends of his intent to betray them into the Hands of Forraign Powers, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to ſend them to fall by the Sword in the <hi>French</hi> King's Service againſt the Confederate Princes, which Letter bares Date <hi>April</hi> 19/27 1677.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Perſons abovementioned, gave the Deponent 10 <hi>l.</hi> to carry the ſaid Letter to Father <hi>Sinman</hi> into the Kingdom of <hi>Spain</hi> to <hi>Madrid,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Sinman</hi> being the Provincial General for the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and in order to which Meſſage, the Deponent Embarked himſelf in the Ship called the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſca</hi> Merchant, whereof <hi>Luke Bath-Roch</hi> was then Maſter to go for <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lboa,</hi> and there took Mules for <hi>Valladolydd,</hi> but ſtaying a day at <hi>Burgos</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> the Deponent broke open the ſaid Letter, and found theſe Contents in the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they of the Society of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seminary at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> ſent a Miſſion of Twelve Students into the Kingdom of <hi>Spain, (viz.)</hi> Eight to <hi>Valladolydd,</hi> and Four to <hi>Madrid,</hi> there being <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colledges in both places in order to Study Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100713:3"/>
and Divinity, which Miſſioners were ſent by <hi>Richard Aſhbey, Richard Peter, Nicholas Blundel,</hi> and <hi>Charles Peter,</hi> by the Patents of the ſeveral Miſſioners, by which they had power to demand Admiſſion into the reſpective Colledges to which they were ſent, which Miſſioners were obliged by the Jeſuits of the Colledges to renounce their Allegiance to His Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> in the hearing of the Deponent, and thoſe of <hi>Valladolydd,</hi> were taught by <hi>Daniel Armeſtrong</hi> a Jeſuite Miniſter of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there. That Firſt the Oath of Allegiance is Heretical and Anti-chriſtian, and Divelliſh, and that <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> King of <hi>England</hi> is no Lawful King, but comes of aſpurious Raſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Father was a Black <hi>Scotch-man,</hi> and not King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt. This was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in a Sermon the <hi>29th.</hi> of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1677. to the Students there, which Sermon the Deponent did hear, and in this Sermon the ſaid <hi>Daniel Armeſtrong</hi> in plain words did ſay, that the King of <hi>England</hi> was a Baſtard; now that <hi>Daniel Armeſtrong</hi> goeth in <hi>Spain</hi> by the Name of <hi>Joſeph Munford,</hi> in <hi>Spaniſh</hi> by <hi>John Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefortio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That the ſaid <hi>John Munford,</hi> alias <hi>Armeſtrong,</hi> did bring Letters from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colledge at <hi>Valladolydd,</hi> to the Father there in <hi>Latin,</hi> by reaſon they were <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in which was expreſſed and related from the Fathers at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> that the Fathers of the Society of <hi>London,</hi> hath procured one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Beningfield,</hi> to be Confeſſor to His Royal Highneſs, but if they ſaw that His Royal Highneſs did not anſwer their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they would diſpoſe of him as they did intend to diſpoſe of His Brother the King, which they hoped to effect within a year, which Letter bares Date, <hi>June</hi> 1677. and Subſcribed by <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> alias <hi>Shimbleby,</hi> Rector of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Jeſuites at St. <hi>Omers, Richard Peter</hi> Miniſter, <hi>Edward Nevil</hi> Prefect of the Studies, <hi>Ch. Peters</hi> Prefect of Sodality, <hi>John Farmor</hi> Prefect of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, which Letters the Deponent ſaw in the Month of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1677. at <hi>Valladolydd</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That Father <hi>Sinman</hi> above mentioned, Writ to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colledge, and the Fathers there ſaid, that the King of <hi>England</hi> was Poyſoned to the great Joy of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fathers, and that they would ſerve King <hi>James</hi> ſo, if he did not give them a good aſſurance of bringing in the Catholick Religion, and of rooting out the Proteſtant, this Letter bore Date <hi>July</hi> the And was ſeen and read by the Deponent at <hi>Valladolydd,</hi> near the latter end of <hi>July,</hi> 1677.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100713:3"/>
            <p n="6">6. That one Father <hi>John Blake,</hi> alias <hi>Croſs,</hi> who went with the Four Students to <hi>Madrid,</hi> did bring Letters from <hi>Richard Strange</hi> Provincial of the Jeſuits, and one Father <hi>Gray</hi> a Jeſuit, and <hi>John Keines,</hi> to Father <hi>Sinman</hi> above mentioned, in which was ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed the great diligence was uſed by the ſaid <hi>Richard Strange,</hi> Father <hi>Gray,</hi> and <hi>John Keines,</hi> to procure ſuch perſons to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch the King, and to put a period to his dayes, which Letter bore date <hi>June</hi> the 10. 1677. <hi>Stilo Novo.</hi> And the Deponent being ſent to <hi>Madrid</hi> in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> read it in Father <hi>Sinmans</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he ſhewing it alſo at the ſame time to <hi>James Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Tuam,</hi> of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. That the ſaid Father <hi>Sinman</hi> received another Letter, <hi>July</hi> the 20. 1677. <hi>Stilo Novo,</hi> from <hi>Richard Strange,</hi> Father <hi>Gray, John Keines, Bazill Longworth, John Fenwick,</hi> Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Father <hi>Hartcourt;</hi> in which they did manifeſt, they were very ſorry for informing him; that he might aſſure himſelf that the buſineſs was done, there man <hi>William</hi> being faint harted, could not then do it, though he had 15000 <hi>l.</hi> promiſed for his pains, of which Letters the Engliſh <hi>Miſſioners</hi> by one information, that at <hi>Madrid</hi> by <hi>John Croſs,</hi> alias <hi>Blake,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Valladolydd,</hi> by <hi>Daniel Armestrong</hi> Jeſuit, which Letters the deponent ſaw in the Chamber of Mr. <hi>Synman,</hi> at <hi>Madrid,</hi> at the ſame time that he ſaw the Letters of the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>June,</hi> mentioned in the fore-going paragraph or num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That on the 3. of <hi>November Stilo Novo,</hi> Father <hi>Petro Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymo de Cordela</hi> Provincial of the Jeſuits in <hi>New Caſtle,</hi> did write to <hi>Richard Strange,</hi> and <hi>John Keines,</hi> that if the buſineſs of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patching of the King of <hi>England</hi> could be effected, they ſhould have 10000 <hi>l.</hi> which Letter the deponent brought from <hi>Vallado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydd</hi> to <hi>Bilboa,</hi> and imbarked in a Ship within 5 dayes after his Arrival thither, and in five dayes more arrived at a little Town near <hi>Exeter,</hi> and in five dayes more at <hi>London,</hi> and delivered the Letter, to <hi>Richard Strange;</hi> and when opened it was writ in Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, and read by the ſaid <hi>Strange;</hi> and he ſaid, that all means ſhould be uſed to anſwer Father <hi>Petro's</hi> expectation; and in the Letter to <hi>Strange</hi> was one incloſed to this <hi>Keines,</hi> by the Name of <hi>John de Neaporto de la Companey de Jeſus,</hi> which Letter the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> offered the Deponent to read, and becauſe of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> abbreviation, the Deponent did not well underſtand the Letter, it being alſo in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue; ſo that the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100713:4"/>
could but make little of it; therefore the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> did give the Deponent the Letter directed to himſelf, ſaying that he thought the Deponent underſtood the Letter better then <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> that the Deponent read the Letter, and found in it the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents above mentioned, and the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> being then ill upon <hi>Stranges</hi> Bed, ſaid, that he hoped that God would ſtrengthen ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>Williams</hi> heart to do this work (now this honeſt <hi>William</hi> is a Servant of the Society of <hi>London)</hi> this <hi>Strange</hi> did lye at Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> his Houſe, part of <hi>Wild-houſe</hi> in <hi>Wild-ſtreet,</hi> where the Deponent heard this diſcourſe, from <hi>Strange</hi> and <hi>Keines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. That the ſaid <hi>Richard Strange, Bazill Longworth,</hi> Father <hi>Hartcourt, John Fenwick,</hi> Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> Father <hi>Gray,</hi> Father <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon,</hi> Father <hi>Saunders,</hi> and Father <hi>Euliſton</hi> did write a Letter, and ſubſcribed it, and did ſend it to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> to <hi>Richard Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,</hi> Alias <hi>Thimbleby,</hi> Rector of the <hi>Engliſh Seminary,</hi> there in which he, and the reſt of the Fathers were given to underſtand, that the King was as well given to Debauchery, as Whoreing, that they had an intent to get one to ſtab him in his Court at Whitehall, and if that could not be conveniently done, they would imploy one of his Phyſitians to Poyſon him, and for his work they had 10000 <hi>l.</hi> in the hands of one <hi>Worſeley</hi> a <hi>Gold-Smith,</hi> which Money was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by one Father <hi>Leſhee</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Jeſuit, and Confeſſor to the <hi>French</hi> King, which Letter the Deponent ſaw and read, and ſaw it ſubſcribed by the above ſaid perſons, and carried them to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> he went down to <hi>Dover</hi> in a Coach, place being taken for him by the ſaid <hi>William</hi> their Servant, but whoſe Name is <hi>John Groves</hi> the Letter carried bore date<hi>—December</hi> 1677. <hi>Stilo Novo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. That Letters were incloſed in this Letter aforementioned, the aforementioned Father <hi>Leſhee,</hi> in which thanks were given him, by the Father that had ſubſcribed the Letter, to Father <hi>Richard Aſhbey</hi> for his great charity to them, and his care for the propagating the <hi>Catholick</hi> Religion, and that all meanes ſhould be uſed to deſtroy the oppoſers of it, both root and branch, which Letters bear date the ſixth or ſeventh day of <hi>December,</hi> which Letters the Deponent carried incloſed with thoſe of <hi>Richard Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey</hi> to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and from St. <hi>Omers</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> and delivered them into the hands of the ſaid <hi>Leſhee,</hi> about the 18. <hi>December.</hi> as near as the Deponent can remember.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That other Letters, bearing date <hi>December.</hi> the 12. 1677.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100713:4"/>
were ſent from <hi>Richard Strange</hi> and others of the Society of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> to thoſe of the Society of the Engliſh Seminaries at St. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> and them Letters were incloſed to Father <hi>Leſhee,</hi> in which they told him they had ſtirred up the Presbyterians in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to a Rebellion, and that 20000 <hi>l.</hi> of them would be in Arms, if that his Majeſtie would break with the King of <hi>England,</hi> and that a way was alſo made for the <hi>French</hi> King landing an Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and further that the <hi>Iriſh Catholicks</hi> were ready to riſe in order, to which 40000 Black Bills, were provided to ſerve the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Souldiers withal, which Letters were ſubſcribed by <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Strange, John Keines,</hi> and <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> and the outſide Letter directed to <hi>Richard Aſhbey</hi> and told the Deponent that the Letter to <hi>Leſhee</hi> was carried by a ſpecial meſſenger, for which he had 10 Pattacoones as the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey,</hi> to the Deponent ſaid, and that the Meſſenger was Drummer of St. <hi>Omers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. That an other Packet ſub-date the 18. of <hi>December</hi> 1677. in which it was ſpecified that the Father <hi>Grall</hi> of the Society of <hi>Jeſus</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> had written and removed <hi>Richard Strange</hi> from being Provincial, and had profered the Provincialſhip on <hi>Thomas Whitebread:</hi> Ordered that Father <hi>Conyers</hi> ſhould Preach on <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi>'s day, in the ſodality Church, in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, againſt the oath of Supremacy and Allegiance, and that he ſhould exhort the Fathers to ſtand by the new Provincial, who would be as zealous for the bringing in of the Catholick Religion into <hi>England,</hi> as ever his Predeceſſors were, and would not leave one ſtone unturned to promote the ſame, which ſaid Letter was directed and read by <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> and this was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 24. of <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. That another Packet Sub-Date the 26. where it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by <hi>Thomas Whitebread, Richard Strange, John Keins, Bazill Longworth, John Fenwick, Francis Gray,</hi> Father <hi>Hartcourt</hi> Senior, Father <hi>Hartcourt</hi> Junior, Father <hi>Michael,</hi> Father <hi>Benefield,</hi> Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> Father <hi>Blundel,</hi> Father <hi>Jeniſon</hi> and ſome others of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; That Father <hi>Leſhee</hi> ſhould be written to by <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> and informed that the Fathers before named had met together, to contrive the advancement of the Deſign of the happy diſpoſal of His Majeſty of Great Britain: and if his Royal Highneſs ſhould not appear to anſwer the expectation, the former giving no hopes at all, they would endeavour with all ſpeed his diſpatch; that he might not hinder their deſign of Bringing in the Catholick Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and if they could not find an opportunity of taking him from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100713:5"/>
his Kingdom, they would take his Kingdom from him: which Letter, he, this Deponent, ſaw in the hands of <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> and deſired to read it, but the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey</hi> would not read it to him, <hi>Jan.</hi> the 2. 1678.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That in the ſaid Letter of <hi>December</hi> the 26. it was ſpecified that <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Blundel</hi> was Conſtituted by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent from the Provincial, to be Ordinary of <hi>Newgate,</hi> to go and viſit the Condemned Priſoners, and to ſeduce them to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, and to Catechize ſome Youths in <hi>London;</hi> and every day in the Week he hath his ſeveral places, where he teaches Youth treaſonable Doctrines, and mutinous againſt the Intereſt, and Perſon of His Sacred Majeſty; and giveth ſeveral ſums of Mony to their Parents, if Poor, to encourage them to ſend their Children to be thus inſtructed, which paſſages was contained in the aforeſaid Letter, and afterwards practiſed in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. That another Packet came to <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> from <hi>Thomas White, John Keines</hi> and others of the Society of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in <hi>London.</hi> Which Letters from them and others were incloſed to Father <hi>Thomas Stapleton</hi> Procurator at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> to perſwade the Father Confeſſor to the Duke <hi>De villa Hermoſa,</hi> to inform him that His Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> did not intend to aſſiſt His Majeſty of <hi>Spain,</hi> but to ſtand a looker on, till he was ruined by the <hi>French</hi> King, which Letter being not ſealed, was ſeen, heard, and by <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> in which it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that if the ſaid Father Confeſſor ſhould not be ready to comply with the ſaid <hi>Stapleton;</hi> that Meſſengers ſhould be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſent to Father <hi>Sinman</hi> at <hi>Madrid,</hi> to inform His Majeſty of <hi>Spain,</hi> of the ſaid concern; and to make the ſame relation of the buſineſs to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Tuam,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> now at the Court of <hi>Madrid.</hi> That he the ſaid Arch-Biſhop, and the ſaid <hi>Sinman,</hi> might jointly give an account to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> of the motion made, or to be made to the ſaid Father Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, to the Duke <hi>De Villa Hermoſa:</hi> and alſo to adviſe the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> King to Seize the Eſtates of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, in ſeveral Factories in this Kingdom. For that they have endeavoured to Tranſport them to <hi>England,</hi> which would tend highly to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of <hi>Spain;</hi> and for the Confirmation whereof, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured Letters from one <hi>Fauſica,</hi> ſometimes an Agent in <hi>London,</hi> to atteſt the ſame. To which the ſaid <hi>Fauſica</hi> willingly conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, and ſent his Letters to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> to be ſent to the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> that the Fathers might give their approbation, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100713:5"/>
Letter was long and large, with atteſtations therein made againſt the Merchants reſidents in their ſeveral Factories, concerning the matter of Faith before mentioned; and alſo other Letters to <hi>Daniel Armſtrong</hi> at <hi>Valladolidd,</hi> and <hi>John Armſtrong</hi> at <hi>Madrid;</hi> which they were ordered to Confirm this affirmation made, or to be made by the Fathers in <hi>England;</hi> and of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries at St. <hi>Omers.</hi> Or if the ſaid <hi>Stapleton,</hi> together with that of <hi>Fauſica</hi> the above mentioned <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Agent, now lives at <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> in <hi>Flanders:</hi> All which Letters bore Date the Firſt, Second of <hi>January,</hi> 1678. <hi>Stilo Novo;</hi> and were ſeen by the Deponent at St. <hi>Omers:</hi> and in the Letters to the Two Fathers, <hi>Armſtrong</hi> and <hi>Croſs</hi> in <hi>Spaein,</hi> was contained a ſpecial Order, that if the fermer could go to <hi>Madrid,</hi> he ſhould ſend his Atteſtation to <hi>Don John of Auſtria,</hi> and to carry on which, 200 <hi>l.</hi> was made over by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sinman</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fathers.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That when the Lords came from <hi>England,</hi> about the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before mentioned to St. <hi>Omers, Edward Nevil,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Farmer</hi> did ſay, that they would not let this Black Baſtard go ſo, to His Grave in peace, meaning the King of <hi>England;</hi> for that he had cheated them ſo often, and that now they reſolved to be ſerved ſo no more. That this Deponent ſtanding by, ſaid if the Duke prove ſlippery, they both replyed that his Pas-Port was ready, when ever he ſhould appear to fail them. Theſe words were heard by the Deponent, on the Third of <hi>January</hi> in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, in the Library of the Jeſuits at St. <hi>Omers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. That on the Fourth of <hi>January</hi> 1678. <hi>Stilo Novo,</hi> Letters were ſent from <hi>Richard Aſhbey, Edward Hall, Edward Novil, Chriſt. Peters, William Busby, James Junior, Thomas Farmer, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael Conſtable</hi> Jeſuits of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seminary at St. <hi>Omers;</hi> as alſo from Father <hi>Williams,</hi> Rector of <hi>Watton,</hi> and Maſter of the Novices there. Sir <hi>Jo. Warner</hi> Barroner, alias <hi>Clare, Franois Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> alias <hi>Ditz-Biling,</hi> to the Father-Confeſſor of the Emperours Majeſty: That His Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain</hi> hath treatherouſly been the ruin of the Confederates; eſpecially, of the <hi>Germain</hi> Empire, and of his Catholick Princes under him, and has under hand ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebellion againſt his Imperial Majeſty, and found them Money to go on in their Rebellion: His deſign being not to keep any Alliance with his Imperial Majeſty; but only in ſhew that he might advance the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> his Nephew, and make him abſolute; and therefore prayed the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> might have notice of it. Which Letter was ſeen, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100713:6"/>
by the Deponent, it being writ in the Latine Tongue. All which Letters were ſent away by a Lay Brother, who was a <hi>Dutch</hi> Man; and when theſe Letters were ſending away, one of the Lay Brothers, whoſe name was <hi>George;</hi> did ſay, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was more fit to Roban Orchard, than to be a General of an Army.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That Letters bearing Date the 1. of <hi>January, Stilo Novo,</hi> arrived at St. <hi>Omers January</hi> the 20. from Arch-Biſhop <hi>Talbot,</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Dubline;</hi> wherein it was expreſſed that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Society in <hi>Ireland,</hi> were very vigilant to prepare the people to riſe, for the defence of their liberty and Religion, and to recover their eſtates; and if the Parliament that was to fit in England, ſhall joyn with the King in declaring war againſt <hi>France,</hi> and ſhould put His Majeſty to ingage in a War with <hi>France,</hi> that a place in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be open to receive the <hi>French</hi> Kings Army, when His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty ſhould think fit to Land one their. And in the Letter he adviſed the Fathers of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> to advertiſe Father <hi>Leſhee</hi> of the ſame, and other Jeſuits that had an intereſt in the <hi>French</hi> King; and that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of Great <hi>Britain</hi> was brought to that paſs, that if any Male content amongſt them ſhould not prove true to their deſigns; His Majeſty would never give ear to their information, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to be diligent, for now was the time, or never. Which Letter this Deponent ſaw and read, and in order to the Fathers Compliance, with the ſaid Arch-Biſhops Letters to Father <hi>Leſhee</hi> to <hi>Paris</hi> and appointed <hi>Edward Nevil,</hi> and <hi>William Busby</hi> to carry, and deliver them to the ſaid <hi>Leſhee,</hi> which Letters were anſwered with all ſpeed by the aforeſaid Meſſengers, Jeſuits, as above. The one of them being Prefect of Studies, and the other Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator for the Seminaries, and by them writ Letters to <hi>Thomas White</hi> Provincial to the Rector of St. <hi>Omers, (viz.) Richard Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,</hi> but of that to the Provincial, the Deponent can give no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; but of that to <hi>Aſhbey,</hi> the Deponent faith, there was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in it, that the General of the Society of the Jeſuits would Contribute 500000. Crowns to be paid in <hi>June</hi> next coming; and that his Holineſs the Pope would not be wanting to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them, when they had made ſome progreſs in that glorious attempt.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That another Packet arrived at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> directed to <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Aſhbey</hi> Rector there, the Date whereof is not well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by this Deponent; but as near as he doth remember, it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100713:6"/>
was about the beginning of the Parliament, for then came the Kings, and Lord Chancellors Speeches, and Votes of Parliament, which were put into ridiculous Phraſes, in contempt of the King and both Houſes of Parliament, and for the Fathers and Scholars to Laugh at, and then Tranſlated into <hi>French,</hi> and given to the Governor of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> who ſent them to the <hi>French</hi> King his Maſter; and in the Packet was contained, the account of the attempt of one <hi>Pickering,</hi> a Lay Brother, that waited on the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites lying at <hi>Sommerſet-houſe,</hi> to Shoot the King as he was Walking in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park, when he was at ſome diſtance from his Nobles, and Attendants, but the Flint of his Piſtol being looſe, he did defer the Action till another opportunity, and if he had done it, and had ſuffered, he ſhould have had 300000. Maſſes ſaid for the Health of his Soul, which Letters were ſigned by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas White,</hi> alias <hi>Whitebread</hi> Provincial: when received, the Fathers of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seminaries, were in great trouble for <hi>Pick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rings</hi> negligence; which Letters the Deponent ſaw and read in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of <hi>January,</hi> and the Votes put into ſuch Mock-Phraſes, as alſo the Kings and Lord Chancellors Speeches, in the Month of <hi>February.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. That the Deponent went out the <hi>29th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> to know of his Confeſſarious, whether he might keep the Thirtieth day of <hi>January</hi> as a Faſt, the Confeſſor replyed, that the account with them was the Ninth of <hi>February,</hi> by reaſon the account with <hi>England</hi> did differ from that on that ſide of the Water, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent then asked if he might keep the Ninth of <hi>February,</hi> the Confeſſarious asked him, why? the Deponent replyed, becauſe of the Martyrdom of the late King<hi>:</hi> He anſwered, the late King was no Martyr, but a Heretick; and withall added, that he was not King <hi>James</hi>'s Son, but a Baſtard, begotten on the Body of Queen <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> by her Taylor; this Confeſſarious is a Jeſuite, and his name is <hi>Charles Peters,</hi> Prefect of the Sodality.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That Letters bearing Date 18. of <hi>February, Stilo Novo,</hi> from <hi>Thomas Whitebread, John Keines, John Fenwick,</hi> Father <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Father <hi>Micho,</hi> Father <hi>Richard Aſhby</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Omers</hi> (then ill of the Gout) to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fathers there, and did let them know, that they had ſent <hi>William Morgan</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſee how Affairs ſtood there in that Kingdom, and expected his return by the end of <hi>March,</hi> and that he ſet out the <hi>26th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> with Inſtructions to order the Affairs in Hand, and to encourage the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Natives to defend their Religion and Liberty,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100713:7"/>
and his Companion was one <hi>Francis Lovell,</hi> who was to go into the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſee the Fathers of the Society there, and carry 2000 <hi>l.</hi> to ſupply their preſent wants, and to promiſe 4000 <hi>l.</hi> in caſe of action.</p>
            <p n="22">22. That another Packet came from <hi>Thomas White,</hi> alias <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread,</hi> Father <hi>Micho,</hi> Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> Father <hi>Hartcourt,</hi> and others of the Society of <hi>London,</hi> bearing Date <hi>Feb.</hi> 7. 1678. in the which was contained, an account of the Fathers Progreſs in <hi>Berk-ſhire, Oxford, Eſſex,</hi> in perſwading the Catholicks, who are Votaries, for the Order of St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> to Contribute to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and maintaining of a Civil War in that Kingdom, in caſe the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould break with the King of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo have received Letters from <hi>Scotland,</hi> in which they were inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the people would riſe to oppoſe Duke <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and the Royal Party in that Kingdom, by which means they thought to weaken both Parties, and alſo that they would endeavor by themſelves, their Agents, and Purſe, to provoke the <hi>Scots</hi> againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and withall, told the Affairs at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> to whom this Packet was directed, and by whom it was read, that they ſhould be glad to effect ſuch a deſign, which Packet the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſaw and read, Letter by Letter.</p>
            <p n="23">23. That the Fathers of St. <hi>Omers, (viz.) Richard Aſhbey</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, <hi>Edward Hall, Edward Nevil,</hi> and others of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary, did Write to <hi>Thomas Whitebread</hi> and other Fathers, in the which it was expreſt, that it was now apparent, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion was to be brought in the ſame way that they had uſed, for the Deſtruction of the Father of this King, and as that could not be effected by the effuſion of Blood, and withall, prayed them to Proſecute their deſign in taking away the King, and if His Royal Highneſs ſhould not comply with them, to diſpatch him alſo, for they did fear that never any of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> were men for the effecting of their ends and purpoſes, and this Letter and Inſtructions, were given to the Fathers, how to feel His Royal Highneſs ſtood affected, which Letter bore Date <hi>February</hi> the Ninth, <hi>Stilo Novo,</hi> and was ſigned by the Perſons aboveſaid, in the preſence of the Deponent, who did Compoſe the ſaid Letters for them, according to Directions given him by them, which Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was (to this Deponents knowledg) carryed into <hi>England,</hi> by one Father <hi>Eury,</hi> who then went thither.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100713:7"/>
            <p n="24">24. That an anſwer of the aforeſaid Letter, <hi>February</hi> the <hi>19th. Stilo Novo,</hi> came Dated the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> from <hi>Thomas White, John Keines, Bazil Longworth, Richard Peters, John Fenwick,</hi> Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> Father <hi>Hartcourt,</hi> Father <hi>Blundel,</hi> Father <hi>Matthew Wright,</hi> Father <hi>Thomas Wright,</hi> Father <hi>Jeniſon,</hi> and Father <hi>Sinman,</hi> who ſome times belong to <hi>Summerſet-houſe,</hi> who alſo Signed with the reſt the ſaid anſwer, which told the Fathers of St. <hi>Omers, (viz.) Richard Aſhbey,</hi> to whom the Letter was Directed, that they found, that although the Duke was a good Catholick, yet he had a tender affection for the King his Brother, and would ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be engaged in the concern, and if they ſhould but once inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the deſigns and purpoſes unto him, they might not only be fruſtrated of their deſign, but alſo might looſe his favor<hi>:</hi> which Letter, the Deponent ſaw and read in <hi>February.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25. That the Fathers of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seminaries at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> did oblige one Brother <hi>George,</hi> a Lay Brother in that Seminary, to go to <hi>Ghent</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> to the <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh</hi> Jeſuites there, with a Letter from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> Dated the <hi>26th.</hi> of <hi>February</hi> from <hi>London,</hi> and the ſaid Brother Arrived there, as they adviſed the Father, the Firſt of <hi>March,</hi> that the Secular Clergy ſhould be Treated with about the buſineſs, but they finding them at that time, to be men inclined to live in Peace and Obedience to their Prince, the Father, with <hi>Thomas White,</hi> &amp;c. anſwered them in one of the Tenth of <hi>March, Stilo Novo.</hi> That the Clergy were a ſort of Raſcally Fellows, that had neither Wit nor Courage, to Manage ſuch a Great Deſign, and did pray them of <hi>Ghent,</hi> and thoſe of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> to be of god Chear, for they went on well, both in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Fatal Blow ſhall be given the Black Boy of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> with all the ſpeed that might; which Letter to them at <hi>Ghent,</hi> and from them, to the Provincial, they being brought to St. <hi>Omers</hi> before they went: as alſo thoſe of <hi>March</hi> the Tenth, the Deponent ſaw and read.</p>
            <p n="26">26. That there was an attempt, to make an aſſaſſination on the Perſon of His Sacred Majeſty, in the Month of <hi>March,</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral days as he was Walking in the Park, and once as he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Parliament-Houſe, by Honeſt <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Pickering,</hi> but opportunity did not offer it ſelf, for the which, the former was Chidden, and the later had a Penance of Twenty ſtroakes, with a Diſcipline on his ſhoulders, it being judged by the Fathers, the effect of his negligence: Which paſſage the Deponent ſaw,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100713:8"/>
mentioned in a Letter, from <hi>Thomas White,</hi> to <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> bearing Date the 26. of <hi>March</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p n="27">27. That on the 5. of <hi>April,</hi> Letters came from <hi>Thomas White,</hi> and the Fathers in <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> and thoſe in St. <hi>Omers,</hi> in the which, the former gives the latter to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that <hi>William Morgan</hi> and Father <hi>Lovel,</hi> were returned out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that they had given them an account, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> was ready to riſe at ten days warning, with Twenty thouſand Foot and Five thouſand Horſe, and would let the <hi>French</hi> King into that Kingdom, if he ſhould come with an Army to land there, and that Father <hi>Lovel</hi> did give an account, that Fifteen thouſand Foot, would riſe in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that the people were patient but very reſolute, and that the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> now Lievt. is in great perplexity to ſee the Catholick Religion thrive ſo well in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that there are perſons, that have Secretly taken Commiſſions from the General of the Society of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by virtue of a Breviate from the <hi>Pope,</hi> Dated <hi>October.</hi> 1673. and that they are reſolved to cutt the Proteſtants Throats once again, when they riſe, and in the ſaid Letter, the Provincial Summoned a General Council, to be holden in <hi>London,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore commanded the Fathers, on the other ſide of the water to be preſent, in which Letter the Deponent, did ſee himſelf to be Summoned to aſſiſt at the Conſultation, as a meſſenger from Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to Fathers, this Letter the Deponent ſaw in the Moneth of <hi>April.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">28. That in order to this Command on <hi>April</hi> the 24. 1678. Father <hi>Warren</hi> Rector of <hi>Liege,</hi> Sir. <hi>Thomas Preſton</hi> Barronet, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>March</hi> Rector of <hi>Ghent,</hi> and Father <hi>Williams</hi> Rector of <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and Maſter of the Novices, Sir. <hi>Jo. Warner</hi> Barronet, <hi>Richard Aſhby</hi> being ſick of the Gout would not go, but out of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary of St. <hi>Omers</hi> went Sir. <hi>Robert Brett</hi> Barronet, Father <hi>Poole, Edward Nevil,</hi> there were in all with the Deponent about nine or ten, who met in <hi>London,</hi> about Conſultation with <hi>Thomas Whitebread,</hi> Father Hartcourt Senior and Junior, <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> Father <hi>Longworth, William Morgan, John Keines,</hi> Father <hi>Lovel,</hi> Father <hi>Ireland, John Blundel, Richard Strange,</hi> Father <hi>Micho,</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Gray,</hi> and others to the number of fifty Jeſuits, met at the White horſe Tavern in the <hi>Strand,</hi> where they plotted their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes for the Society, and ordered Father <hi>John Gray</hi> (who was always there) to go Procurator for <hi>Rome,</hi> all which conſultations they held in <hi>May,</hi> 1678. The Deponent was preſent to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100713:8"/>
the conſultory, and did their concerns from Company to Company, ſome met at Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> houſe in <hi>Wildſtreet,</hi> others at Mr. <hi>Fenwicks,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Ayres</hi> houſe in <hi>Drury Lain,</hi> others at Mr. <hi>Ireland</hi>'s in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> and other places, all which though in ſeveral Companies did contrive the death of the King, in order to which Papers were ſent from Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to Company, which the Deponent did carry containing their opinion of the buſineſs and the manner how it was to be done, and within three or four days after, the Deponent went to St. <hi>Omers</hi> with the Fathers, who came from the other ſide of the water.</p>
            <p n="29">29. <hi>Item</hi> that on the 10. of <hi>June Stilo Novo,</hi> came <hi>Tho. White</hi> Provincial of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and in order to viſit his Colledges in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and in his Chamber of the tenth day, when the Deponent with <hi>Richard Aſhbey</hi> were preſent, he told the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey</hi> and the Deponent, that he hoped to ſee the Fool at <hi>Whitehall</hi> laid faſt enough, and that the Society need not fear, for he (that is the King) is grown—and would hear no complaint againſt them, and if the Duke ſhould ſee his face in the leaſt manner to follow his Brothers foot ſteps, his pasport was made to lay him aſleep.</p>
            <p n="30">30. <hi>Item</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Thomas Whitebread,</hi> on the Thirteenth of <hi>June,</hi> did tell the Rector of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> that there was a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that had Scandalouſly and baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put out the Jeſuits Morals in <hi>England,</hi> and had indevoured villanouſly to render them odious to the people, and asked the ſaid Rector whether the Deponent might poſſibly know him, and the Rector not knowing called the Deponent, who heard theſe words as he ſtood at the door, wherein being entred, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial asked the Deponent, if he knew him that was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Jeſuits Morals, his Perſon but not his Name: The ſaid <hi>Thomas Whitebread</hi> demanded then, whether the Deponent would undertake to Poyſon or Aſſaſſmate the ſaid Author, which the Deponent undertook to do, and to have 500 <hi>l.</hi> reward promiſed him by the Provincial, and appointed to return to <hi>England,</hi> and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent doth further teſtify, that at the ſame time, the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial did in his Chamber ſay, that he and the Society in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> would procure Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> to be knockt in the head, and alſo <hi>Poole</hi> the Author of <hi>Synopſis criticorum,</hi> for writing ſomething againſt them.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100713:9"/>
            <p n="31">31. <hi>Item</hi> That <hi>Richard Aſhbey</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> being ill that evening with the Gout and Stone <hi>(viz)</hi> the 15. of <hi>June,</hi> he deſired the company of the Deponent, and did tell him, that Father <hi>Warren</hi> now Rector of the Jeſuits Colledge in <hi>Leige,</hi> did when he was Procurator at <hi>Paris,</hi> Reconcile the late Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celor Hide to the Church of Rome, upon his Death-bed, which words were occaſioned by the Deponents taking notice that the late Dutches of <hi>York</hi> (the Lord Chancelors Daughter) dyed a Papiſt, and the Deponent, when he heard the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey</hi> ſpeak theſe words, replyed, that he never had heard any thing of the return of the Lord Chancellor, anſwer was made that the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey</hi> was certain that the Lord Chancellor was reconciled by the ſaid <hi>Warren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="32">32. That the 23 of <hi>June Stilo Novo,</hi> in the afternoon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, had expreſs order preſently to repair to <hi>Callis,</hi> and then take the Packet Boat, and ſo away for <hi>England,</hi> to attend the motions of the Fathers in <hi>London,</hi> till he had orders from the Provincial to the contrary, and gave the Deponent four pounds for his Charges, and promiſed him 80 <hi>l.</hi> for ſervice already done, for the Society in <hi>Spain</hi> and elſewhere, and the Deponent ſaith that night he parted for <hi>Callis,</hi> where he met four Jeſuits bound for <hi>London,</hi> on <hi>Fryday</hi> they all took Boat, on <hi>Saturday</hi> they arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Dover,</hi> where they met <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> who had brought Students to <hi>Dover,</hi> to tranſport them to St. <hi>Omers.</hi> The Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſaith further that the four Jeſuits, <hi>John Fenwick</hi> (who went at <hi>Dover</hi> by the name of Mr. <hi>Tompſon)</hi> and himſelf took Coach, and that at Burton ſix miles this ſide <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Coach was ſtopt and a Box was ſeized, of the ſaid <hi>John Fenwicks,</hi> by the Searchers of the place, and when by them opened, in it, they found Beads, Pictures, Images, and other <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> which were to be given by Bundles, the Catechiſe to Children to encourage them, to come to Catechiſing School, and to be Catechiſed by him, according there was a direction to him, fixed on the Box, to the Honorable <hi>Richard Blundel</hi> Eſquire in <hi>London,</hi> which Box ſo ſeized by the ſaid Searchers, and they had ſearched the Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets of the ſaid <hi>Fenwick,</hi> they had found ſuch Letters about him, as he confeſſed to the Deponent, might have coſt him his Life, they (calling ſaid he) the concern in hand, but the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the Deponent did not ſee.</p>
            <p n="33">33. <hi>Item</hi> that in the Moneth of <hi>July, Richard Aſhbey</hi> came to <hi>London,</hi> with inſtructions from the ſaid <hi>Thomas Whitebread,</hi> or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100713:9"/>
               <hi>White,</hi> that the 10000 <hi>l.</hi> procured by Father <hi>Leſhee,</hi> and in the hands of the Society in <hi>London,</hi> ſhould be ſent into the hands of one <hi>Worſely</hi> their Banker, and that the ſaid Richard <hi>Aſhbey,</hi> with other Fathers, ſhould agree with Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> about the Poyſoning the King, and if that he would undertake it, he ſhould have 10000 <hi>l.</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Richard Aſhbey</hi> told the Deponent, ſhewing him the ſaid inſtructions, by way of <hi>memorandum,</hi> in writing, in the which <hi>memorandum</hi> was contained, an <hi>Item</hi> given by the ſaid <hi>Thomas Whitebread,</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> for the aſſaſſination of the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>Herbert,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and for that the ſaid had been educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Popiſh Religion, and was fallen, and they were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that they would not ſpare any Apoſtate from the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith; the ſaid <hi>Richard Aſhbey</hi> asked the Deponent, whether the ſaid Biſhop was a forward man againſt Catholicks, to which the Deponent not knowing the ſaid Lord Biſhop, ſaid, he could not tell, and the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey</hi> did ſay, the times now being ready to Change, they would be ready to puniſh Apoſtates, but all thoſe Hereticks, that had obſtinately oppoſed the proceedings of the Society, and their Agents in propagating the Faith and intereſt of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> a juſt reward for their obſtinacy and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, and though the Parliament had taken away the Act for Burning Hereticks, yet they ſhould not eſcape the vengeance of Catholicks.</p>
            <p n="34">34. <hi>Item</hi> That in the Moneth of <hi>July,</hi> 1678. <hi>Richard Strange</hi> late Provincial of the Jeſuits, came to the Lodging of Mr. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Aſhbey,</hi> who before he went down to the Bath, lay in the new Provincials Lodgings at Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> his houſe, and finding the Deponent with the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey,</hi> did deſire him, the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to meet him at his Chamber, at Mr. <hi>John Groves</hi> in <hi>York-ſtreet,</hi> and after a very ſhort ſtay with him, took his leave of the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey,</hi> and the Deponent, took his leave alſo and followed the ſaid <hi>Strange,</hi> and got to his Chamber preſently after him, where the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> did encourage the Deponent, to go on in aſſiſting the Society, in carrying on the deſign, and thereupon told the Deponent, that they got 14000 <hi>l.</hi> by the Fire in <hi>London,</hi> in 1666. the Deponent asked the ſaid <hi>Strange,</hi> how they came to Effect that great and famous Work, the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> replyed, that himſelf, one <hi>Gray,</hi> one <hi>Pennington,</hi> and one <hi>Burton</hi> Jeſuits, and ſome others, with one <hi>Kinmaſh</hi> a Dominican, Joyned with one <hi>Green,</hi> that met at one Mr. <hi>Weſts</hi> houſe at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> at <hi>Puddle-Dock,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Weſt</hi> was a Taylor, whom they imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100713:10"/>
to make them ſome Cloaths, and there they did debate the manner about the Firing the City, and where they ſhould begin, and did attempt it in <hi>February</hi> 1664/5. But then not being provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with aſſiſtance enough, loſt that good opportunity; becauſe <hi>Downe</hi> and he being afraid to be killed, ran away. This was the greateſt Plunder of one ſort they got, (as the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Deponent) there was a 1000. Carrats of Diamonds rapt in ſeveral Papers, for ſeveral Goldſmiths; but they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed by the firſt opportunity to St. <hi>Omers:</hi> The Deponent ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Strange</hi> how One Man ſhould truſt them with ſo much Goods, and never One Man had ſo much Jewels at once. The ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> ſaid, he could not tell that; but certain it was they met with them, and ſold them for 3500 l. ſterling in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and had a Fiſh Dinner into the Bargain, at the <hi>Salutation</hi> Tavern in <hi>Holbourn,</hi> at the return of the Money. The Deponent asked <hi>Strange,</hi> how the Fire began: The Deponent farther asked <hi>Strange</hi> how many ſervants the Society imployed; and he ſaid about 80. or 86. he could not tell which, he the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> ſaid far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that indeed they were reſolved to have Cut off the King, when at work in Perſon about the Fire; but then they were not got ſecure of the Duke, who was then but a well-wiſher of theirs; and beſides<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſeeing the King ſo Induſtrious, they could not find in their Hearts do it. Whilſt this diſcourſe in hand, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman knockt at the Door, and ſo we broke off; being Nine of the Clock, and ended at almoſt Eleven in the Forenoon, and the Deponent went to his Lodging in <hi>Drury-lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35. <hi>Item,</hi> That <hi>Richard Aſhbey,</hi> the day before he went down to the Bath, which was in <hi>July,</hi> had a Conference with Father <hi>Hartcourt,</hi> Father <hi>Fenwick,</hi> Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> Father <hi>Keines,</hi> Father <hi>Strange,</hi> Father <hi>Jeniſon,</hi> Father <hi>Blundel,</hi> and others of the Society, by Order of the Provincial, to ſend new Meſſengers into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to promote the Commotion there, and to informe the People of the great Tyranny they lye under; by reaſon of their being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the liberty of their Conſciences, and that not to be procured but by the Sword<hi>:</hi> they muſt take that courſe to purchaſe their Liberty; by which means (ſaid the Fathers thus aſſembled) we ſhall weaken both the Presbyterian, and the Epiſcopal party: at which Conference the ſaid Deponent was preſent, and heard theſe words.</p>
            <p n="36">36. <hi>Item,</hi> That in <hi>July</hi> the ſaid <hi>Richard Aſhbey</hi> went down to Bath, in Order to his being Cured for the Gout; and the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100713:10"/>
that he went away, the Deponent being in the Chamber, to take his leave of him, Father <hi>Hartcourt</hi> Rector of <hi>Lond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> came to him, and told him that if after he left the Bath, he would make a little progreſs into <hi>Sommerſetſhire,</hi> to informe thoſe of the Society of the deſign, it would do well; and withal deſired the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey</hi> to haſten to Town, after he had finiſhed the ſaid Information, which the Deponent did hear.</p>
            <p n="37">37. <hi>Item,</hi> That on the Firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Letters from <hi>Thomas Whitebread,</hi> bearing Date the 22. of <hi>July,</hi> to <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> in which it was expreſſed; that if 10000 l. would not do, he would have 15000 l. ſhould be propoſed for the effecting of the Kings death; and that 150000 l. ſhould be propoſed to Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> if he ſhould refuſe the 10000 l. But whether Sir <hi>George</hi> hath been Treated about the Concern, the Deponert cannot as yet inform in this Article; but Sir <hi>George</hi> was divers times in <hi>Aſhbey</hi>'s Company, as the Deponent was informed by the ſaid <hi>Aſhbey;</hi> and ſaw the Letters ſent to <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> Three days after, which was the Fourth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> That Letters arrived in <hi>London,</hi> bearing Date, the Fifth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1678. from <hi>Thomas White</hi> Provincial, to <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> in the which, he did inform the Fathers, that he had made his Viſit within his promiſe; and that he Ordered Twelve Jeſuits to go for <hi>Holland,</hi> and Inform the <hi>Dutch,</hi> that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> did intend to Aſſume the Crown of a King, and that he was reſolved to bring them under another Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which Miſſioners took their leave of the ſaid <hi>Thomas White,</hi> on <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s day, the 31. of <hi>July;</hi> but got no further than <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> by reaſon of a Miſchance they met withal in the way; by which Miſſioners the ſaid <hi>Thomas White,</hi> did deſign to beget in the <hi>Dutch</hi> an evil Opinion of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and to cauſe a Commotion there againſt the Prince: Which Letter, the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſaw, and read in <hi>Fenwicks</hi> Chamber, the Eleventh of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p n="39">39. <hi>Item,</hi> That another Letter of the Maſter of the <hi>Auguſtins</hi> came to <hi>Blundel,</hi> and becauſe the <hi>Thames</hi> was Frozen over, and the Sickneſs coming on, they altered their purpoſe, and in <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> 1675/6. they met with this <hi>Green</hi> again, who cloſed with them in their deſign; and that they might Ingratiate themſelves the more with him, furniſhed him with Thirty Pound (he being Poor, yet they found him an Active Man, and fit for their purpoſe)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100713:11"/>
and the more to ingage the ſaid <hi>Green,</hi> they pretended to hold many Fifth-Monarchy Mens Principles; which when <hi>Green</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived (Judging them too zealous) brought them acquainted with Eight others, who were zealous in the buſineſs. The afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> were earneſt to have the buſineſs done in <hi>February,</hi> before the return of the Inhabitants to <hi>London:</hi> But the ſaid <hi>Green</hi> intreated them to ſuſpend that reſolution; becauſe that they ſhould be the ſooner diſcovered, and ſuch a deſign muſt have an uproar; and beſides that the King would not be much in Town (if at all) until the Plague was more abated; whom the ſaid <hi>Green</hi> did ſay muſt be Cut off too, when the People were in a hurry, by reaſon of the Fire; and this Motion pleaſed the Jeſuits and Dominicans well; and it was put off in a very little time after the ſaid <hi>Green,</hi> and the reſt of the Fifth-Monarchy Men, together with thoſe Four Jeſuits above named; and the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicans were ſuſpected by the ſaid <hi>West,</hi> that kept the houſe at <hi>Puddle-dock,</hi> and were forewarned the ſaid houſe; and preſently after <hi>Green</hi> and his Eight acquaintance were clapt up in Priſon: But for what the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> did not tell the ſaid Deponent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Impriſonment of theſe Nine Perſons. The ſaid Jeſuits did go to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and remain there till <hi>May,</hi> after the Execution of Eight of theſe aforeſaid Perſons <hi>(Green</hi> dying in <hi>Newgate)</hi> one <hi>Fitz-Gerard</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Man and Jeſuit, and one <hi>Neal</hi> of <hi>White-Chappel</hi> did write to this <hi>Strange,</hi> as the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> informed the Deponent, that none of the Fathers names were mentioned in the buſineſs of theſe men, and thought they might ſafely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſo. In the latter part of <hi>May,</hi> they ſet forth for <hi>England,</hi> and got to <hi>London</hi> the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> and then concealing their Names and Lodgings, they began afreſh to conſult about this Fire, which was ſtill carried on by the Jeſuits in <hi>London,</hi> in the abſence of the ſaid Perſons, and it was plotted by them in the Fire-time, to Cut off the King, that the number of the Beaſt might be accompliſhed (in the uttering of which words, the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> broke out into a great Laughter) but ſaid the ſaid <hi>Strange;</hi> To be ſhort, we got 50. or 60. Jeſuits to ply the work, and one <hi>Everard</hi> was very diligent in preſerving the Fire-Balls, which they had made, and put into <hi>Granada-ſhells;</hi> and the more to Palliate this, they procured this <hi>Everard</hi> a Place in the Kings Service, to look after the Ammunition that was to be carried down to the Fleet, it being in the time of the Firſt <hi>Dutch</hi> War; and the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> told the Deponent that great Attempts we made at the <hi>Tower,</hi> but without effect. But ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> to the return, ordering our Affairs, we were alſo in Fee with ſeveral
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100713:11"/>
               <hi>French</hi> men; who, alſo were faithful in the buſineſs; and all things being ready, and the place pitched upon, <hi>Strange</hi> removes his Quarters, and got to lye in a houſe in <hi>Fanchurch-ſtreet,</hi> and went by the name of <hi>Walker;</hi> this he did in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1666. and with him he took the aforeſaid <hi>Kinmaſh</hi> the Dominican together with <hi>Pennington</hi> and <hi>Purton,</hi> who lay at an Apothecaries houſe in <hi>Shooe-lane,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Fitz-Gerrard</hi> lay at <hi>Neales</hi> in <hi>Whitechappel;</hi> but <hi>Neale</hi> was one to ſee the Fire carried on through <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Tower.</hi> In a word, the ſaid <hi>Strange</hi> told the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, they ſpent 700. Fire-Balls; and when the Fire-Merchants were at work, then others (both Men and Women) were at work to Plunder what they could; and that they had a Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in <hi>Wildſtreet,</hi> where ſome things ſo plundered were laid, and other things they concealed in <hi>Sommerſet-houſe,</hi> as Holland, Cambrick, Fine Cloth, and ſome conſiderable quantities of Plate, and a Box of Jewels, the Owners gave their Men to carry away, and ordered his Servant to go along with him; but they having increaſed their number ordered the Servant to be knocked down by the Fathers in <hi>London,</hi> for not giving an account of what progreſs they made, or to be made in the propoſals to Sir <hi>George Wakeman;</hi> and how he refuſed it, if made, and if not, to do it; for it would not be convenient to deferr it, and told them that <hi>Ireland</hi> was ſafely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> arrived at St. <hi>Omers:</hi> Who only told that the King was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſecure; and therefore he the Provincial, admoniſhed them to be very vigilant; which Letter, the ſaid <hi>Blundel</hi> ſhewed the Deponent, the 19. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p n="40">40. <hi>Item,</hi> That another Packet of the 15. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> from <hi>Thomas White</hi> Provincial, to Father <hi>John Fenwick;</hi> in the which were Letters incloſed to Father <hi>Jeniſon,</hi> Father <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court</hi> and others, which Letters he did not ſee; but that to <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> the Deponent ſaw and read; and in it the ſaid <hi>Thomas White</hi> did write, that he hoped that the Figure 365. ſhould lie as low as ever 666. did; and that if Poyſon did not take the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Fire ſhould, for the Catholick Religion would never flouriſh, unleſs <hi>I. H. S.</hi> took its Courſe. Now the Deponent ſaith, that the Figure 365. is meant <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and by 666. <hi>London;</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Character or Cypher for thoſe places; and the Letters <hi>I. H. S.</hi> Jeſuits, they uſing it always.</p>
            <p n="41">41. That the Deponent was informed by <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Society then in his Chamber; that the Jeſuits had 60000 l. <hi>per annum</hi> good Rents, and 100000 l. in Bank; that he and the reſt of the Society, have in the name of their ſeveral
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100713:12"/>
Truſtees, lent Money out at 5 <hi>l.</hi> per cent, the improvement of which Money in Bank, is uſed about theſe practices, and that it coſteth them 400 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> for intelligence, beſides their day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meſſengers (on which vaſt ſumms of Money are ſpent) and beſides, an other part is tranſported beyond-Sea, by Bills of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, which the Deponent (in a very great part) knoweth himſelf to be true, and of the reſt, they themſelves have inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſeveral times, all which tends much to the dammage of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="42">42. <hi>Item,</hi> That on <hi>Munday</hi> 5/15 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Father <hi>Hartcourt, John Keines, John Fenwick,</hi> and another of the Society (whoſe names the Deponent remembers not) did ſay, they intended to raiſe a commotion in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> which alſo did appear by ſeveral Letters, which the Deponent did ſee and read, the Date whereof the Deponent doth not know, nor now well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, but he ſaw them in <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="43">43. <hi>Item,</hi> That Two New Meſſengers were ſent into <hi>Scotland,</hi> on the Fifth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> one by the name of Father <hi>More,</hi> the other Father <hi>Saunders</hi> alias <hi>Brown,</hi> with inſtructions to carry themſelves like Presbyterian Miniſters, and to Preach to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected <hi>Scots,</hi> and the neceſſity of taking up the ſword, for the defence of liberty of Conſcience, theſe the Deponent ſaw diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ordered to go by Father <hi>Hartcourt,</hi> in the name of <hi>Tho. White</hi> Provincial.</p>
            <p n="44">44. <hi>Item,</hi> They have ſeveral times communicated (and doe ſtill) what they have revealed to them of the Kings Secrets: Which they purchaſe by giving Money, and then ſend them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to <hi>Leſhee</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Kings Confeſſor, and the Deponent hath ſeen ſeveral particulars (as others pretend) how the King ſtands affected to War or Peace, and this they do by one <hi>Smith,</hi> who dayly lurketh about Whitehall and Weſtminiſter Hall, in time of Parliament, and is (as he ſaith) in Fee with the Clerks of the Parliament, who gives him the intelligence, and with the Clerks and Officers, of his Majeſties Privy Council, and Cabinet Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. The Deponent ſaith further, that one <hi>Coleman</hi> doth aſſiſt this <hi>Smith</hi> with private intelligence, as <hi>John Keines</hi> Jeſuit, and this <hi>Smith</hi> have told this Deponent, ſeveral times in the Moneths of <hi>July</hi> and <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p n="45">45. <hi>Item,</hi> That theſe Jeſuits drive ſeveral Trades in Town, as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100713:12"/>
Merchants, Tobacconiſts, Gold-Smiths, Scriveners, and by means of the laſt, come to the knowledge of ſeveral Eſtates, of ſeveral Perſons of Quality, and other Scriveners of their Religion and Practices, by which they take an eſtimate of the ſtrength of the Nation, as this Deponent was informed by <hi>John Keines</hi> in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and 'tis probable their Scriveners have great Imployment.</p>
            <p n="46">46. <hi>Item,</hi> That on <hi>Fryday</hi> the Ninth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Came Letters of the Sixteenth <hi>Ditto,</hi> by an eſpecial Meſſenger from <hi>Thomas White</hi> Provincial, and ſubſcribed by the Fathers of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> in which, he and they did rejoyce very much, that Sir <hi>George Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had taken the buſineſs into his hands, and if he did it the 15000. pound ſhould be paid, but ordered that <hi>Pickering</hi> and his companion honeſt <hi>William,</hi> ſhould not deſiſt their endeavoring to Aſſaſſinate the Kings Perſon, which Letters, the Deponent read and asked <hi>Fenwick,</hi> how the Provincial came to underſtand that Sir. <hi>George</hi> had undertaken the buſineſs, he the ſaid <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> told the Deponent, that he had diſpatched a ſpecial Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger away, to give him notice, and that the ſaid Meſſenger brought this Anſwer, and withal ſaid <hi>Fenwick,</hi> it coſt at leaſt Ten Pound to give him word of it.</p>
            <p n="47">47. <hi>Item,</hi> That one <hi>Wil. Berry</hi> (now a ſecular Prieſt,) that had formerly been a Jeſuit, becauſe that the ſaid <hi>Berry</hi> had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and was about to Print ſome ſheets of Paper, in vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, and in it perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, to a more charitable complyance with the Proteſtants; <hi>Bazil Longworth</hi> and others did offer it to the Deponent, to kill the ſaid <hi>Berry,</hi> and if he durſt not do it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to procure ſome others to do it, aſſuring the Deponent, who ever did it ſhould have a pardon. This was propoſed <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Ninth 1678.</p>
            <p n="48">48. That on the Ninth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the Evening, in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>John Keines</hi> Jeſuit, in <hi>Warkwickstreet,</hi> where <hi>John Fenwick</hi> a Jeſuit, and the Deponent were together, there came one <hi>Richard Heath,</hi> a Lay Brother of the Jeſuits, who after ſome diſcourſe, of the deſign of Killing the King, did ſay he was a Baſtard, and indeavored to Rule by the Sword, which words the Deponent did hear, and ſo did <hi>Keines</hi> and <hi>Fenwick,</hi> and replyed one after another in the hearing of the Deponent, that the Baſtard ſhould not trouble the World long.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100713:13"/>
            <p n="49">49. That on the 10/20 <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Deponent did meet with <hi>John Groves,</hi> In <hi>Wild-ſtreet</hi> in the afternoon (as near as he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) about Five a Clock, and <hi>Groves</hi> having made ſeveral promiſes to the Deponent, to give an account of <hi>South-wark</hi> Fire in 1676. The ſaid <hi>Groves</hi> took the Deponent into <hi>Wild-houſe</hi> Garden, and and thus began, he ſaid, that he had certain Fire-works made for that very purpoſe, and he and Three <hi>Iriſh</hi> Men more, that were his aſſiſtants, went into the Burrow, and not finding an opportunity, went to St. <hi>Margarets Hill,</hi> where they found an Oyl-ſhop, which the ſaid <hi>Groves</hi> bragged he Fired; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent asked <hi>Groves,</hi> how he came acquainted with theſe Three <hi>Iriſh</hi> Men, he ſaid his acquaintance was not much, but they were procured by <hi>Foggerly</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Doctor: For which the Society <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Strange</hi> Provincial, gave him and his Aſſiſtants 1000 <hi>l. Viz.</hi> 400 <hi>l.</hi> for him, and 200 <hi>l.</hi> a piece for the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Groves</hi> told the Deponent, that the Society got at leaſt 1000 <hi>l.</hi> in the Fire, which was alſo told the Deponent another time by <hi>Richard Strange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="50">50. That on the 15. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> (Sunday) this Deponent ſaw Letters from St. <hi>Omers, Ditto</hi> vvritten by Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the name of the Provincial <hi>Thomas Whitebread,</hi> to <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> in which Letter (by the contents thereof) there was Letters to <hi>John Keines,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jeniſon, Blundel</hi> and others, which the Deponent did not ſee, but in that to <hi>John Fenwick</hi> it was ſpecified, what diligence was uſed in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Jeſuits there, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and for the procuring another demonſtration of zeale, for the promoting of the Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and intereſt in that Kingdom, and that which arts would not effect, the Sword ſhould, to the great vexation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants there, and he intimated to the greateſt joy he had, that there was yet hopes, the diſaffected <hi>Scots</hi> would not lay aſide their endeavors for, and after the defence of their Liberties and Religion, and that the Catholicks in <hi>Scotland,</hi> had promiſed to uſe their Utmoſt Indeavors to keep up the Commotion there, and the ſaid Father <hi>Ireland,</hi> bad the ſaid Father <hi>Fenwick</hi> to exhort the Fathers there, to be earneſt in their deſign, for now was the time that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, was to be reduced. And further more, ordered (in the name of the Provincial) that Letters ſhould be written to all the Societies in <hi>England,</hi> that they make it their buſineſs, to incourage their friends to braveneſs of mind, for that God had hitherto given them ſuch a hopeful Proſpect of things, and that no opportunity on his part ſhould be loſt, and that they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100713:13"/>
In <hi>London</hi> (if they thought fit to communicate theſe things) that they ſhould have a care, that they did it not to more then one at a time, leaſt they ſhould be bafled in their Enterpriſe, which Letter (when read by the Deponent) <hi>Fenwick</hi> to whom the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was directed, told the Deponent, it was his duty to offer up a Maſs or Two, that God would proſper the deſign of theſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavors of the Society, to promote the Catholick Religion and Faith, and told the Deponent further, that if he lived till <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> he ſhould ſee a good change of things, either that 48. ſhould be taken from the World (or the World, eſpecially that little World he was concerned in) ſhould be taken from him, and that one that was a Catholick ſhould play ſuch a Game, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was play'd ſince the Conqueſt. All which the ſaid <hi>Fenwick,</hi> told the Deponent in his Chamber, and the Deponent asked the ſaid <hi>Fenwick,</hi> who this Catholick was, and the ſaid <hi>Fenwick</hi> ſaid it was the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and the Deponent ſaid 48. is put for the King.</p>
            <p n="51">51. <hi>Item,</hi> on the 21. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the Evening, the Deponent went to the Lodging of <hi>John Keines,</hi> where he found another Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit with him (whoſe name this Deponent remembers not) in whoſe preſence the ſaid <hi>John Keines</hi> told the Deponent, that his Provincial had taken great care, for keeping alive the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces between the diſaffected <hi>Scots,</hi> and Duke <hi>Lautherdale,</hi> and that the Affairs in <hi>Ireland</hi> went on with great expedition, and that meanes was now uſed, to create a difference between the <hi>Dutch</hi> and Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and if it could be effected, there was no queſtion to be made, but that the Proteſtant intereſt would fail in <hi>Holland,</hi> and that 48. would not laſt long in <hi>England,</hi> for that it was high time to hinder 49. from being effected, that Barley Broath trade ſhould grow dead, and Twelve be cut off; that <hi>Mum</hi> and <hi>Chocholate</hi> ſhould be put down, and the order of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies</hi> ſhould be turned into their firſt inſtitution and habit, now the Deponent ſaith theſe words to hinder 49. to be effected, is an odd expreſſion amongſt them, for the cutting off the King, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be 49. Years Old compleat, Barly Broath is the Houſe of Commons, which ſhall be turned out, and ſit no more, <hi>Mum</hi> and <hi>Chocholate</hi> is Proteſtant perſons which if not deſtroyed, ſhall never have any vote in the Houſe of <hi>Peers</hi> after this Kings death, and by the <hi>Magpies</hi> they underſtand the Biſhops, whoſe habit in Parliament is Black and White, which ſhall be turned into Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whilſt the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> and the other Jeſuit entertained this Deponent with theſe Treaſonable diſcourſes and expreſſions, Mr.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100713:14"/>
               <hi>Jeniſon</hi> came to the ſaid <hi>Keines,</hi> and told him he loſt a Letter, which he had received from <hi>Thomas White</hi> the Provincial of St. <hi>Omers</hi> in a Walk he took to <hi>Iſlington,</hi> and would give Ten Pound to any friend that would give it to him, and was afraid ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies would follow, if found by ſome <hi>Heretick;</hi> which words put the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> into ſuch a Conſternation, that he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him if he had a mind to ruin them all; but then the ſaid <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon</hi> bad the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> to be quiet, for none could under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, which word this Deponent did likewiſe hear.</p>
            <p n="52">52. <hi>Item,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Keines</hi> was on the Twelfth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> determined to go to <hi>Windſor,</hi> in Order to ſettle buſineſs therein, and towards the diſpatching 48. at <hi>Windſor,</hi> if the King ſhould go thither; and it was Judged the ſaid 48. would in few days go to <hi>Windſor,</hi> to make his abode there for ſome Weeks; but the ſaid <hi>John Keines</hi> told this Deponent he might chance to fall ſhort of his return again; theſe words were ſpoken to the Deponent by <hi>John Keines</hi> in his Chamber; but the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> did not then go down to <hi>Windſor</hi> ſo ſoon, as afterwards appeared to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent.</p>
            <p n="53">53. <hi>Item,</hi> That <hi>Smith</hi> within mentioned, that lyeth in <hi>Drury-Lane,</hi> at one Mr. <hi>Lowdes</hi> houſe a Taylor, in <hi>Cock-pit Alley</hi> in the aforeſaid Lane; and is alſo imployed to go from Houſe to Houſe, to ſee how the Catholicks ſtand affected, and Mr. <hi>Jeniſon</hi> did ſay, that if the Catholicks had Courage enough, they might Riſe and Cut the Throats of 100000. Proteſtants in <hi>London;</hi> of which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>Jeniſon,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> did tell the Deponent, asking his Opinion alſo of the ſame; he anſwered, that Mr. <hi>Jeniſon</hi> talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like a Perſon that had more heat than light. The ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> did at the ſame time tell the Deponent, that the Society gave him Five Pound <hi>per cent.</hi> for his Intelligence he getteth at Court of the Kings Actions, words, and Council, and tranſmits the ſame to <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> who doth the like to St. <hi>Omers;</hi> where it is Tranſlated into <hi>French,</hi> and ſo goes to Father <hi>Leſhee</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor to the <hi>French</hi> King; which daily Intelligence, the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent did daily ſee from the ſaid <hi>Smith,</hi> he Lodging in the ſame houſe with the Deponent, and the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> at the ſame time did tell the Deponent he was a Lay Brother of the Society of Jeſus, of the Order of Politicians, as they term it, and attends Father <hi>Blundel</hi> to <hi>Newgate,</hi> in Order to Convert the Priſoners there: All which the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> did tell the Deponent, the 12. of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> and likewiſe the ſaid <hi>Blundel</hi> did tell as much to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100713:14"/>
Deponent, who hath ſeen the ſaid <hi>Blundel</hi> and <hi>Smith</hi> go to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> together.</p>
            <p n="54">54. <hi>Item,</hi> That one <hi>Matthew Medbourn</hi> a Player in the Dukes Theatre, one Mr. <hi>Penny,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mammock,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sharpe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Shedon,</hi> and one <hi>Willim Smith</hi> a Schoolmaſter at <hi>Iſlington,</hi> one <hi>Edward Everard,</hi> and others meeting in a Club on <hi>Thurſday</hi> and <hi>Sunday</hi> Nights, with one <hi>Jones</hi> a Prieſt, and one <hi>Kinmaſh</hi> within mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: All theſe Perſons are employed by the Jeſuits to Villifie the Houſe of Commons, and to go about the City of <hi>London,</hi> to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the people againſt them, and againſt the Biſhops of the Nation; and they delivered this Treaſonable Poſition, that the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, are the Devils repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and not the Nations; which Treaſonable and deteſtable words, this Deponent did hear at the ſaid Club, which is kept in <hi>Fullers Rents</hi> near <hi>Grays Inn,</hi> in the Month of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> and the Deponent was Ordered by the Jeſuits in <hi>London,</hi> to give the ſaid Perſons great reſpect, and in their Names to thank the Club for their faithfulneſs to them in that Particular.</p>
            <p n="55">55. <hi>Item,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Jeniſon</hi> on the Twelfth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> did ſay, and did boaſt that he had put ſeveral out of Love with the Kings Intereſt, and would ſo continue, if that the King did not Turn Roman Catholick; and if the King did not become Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, he would not be <hi>Charles Rex</hi> long.</p>
            <p n="56">56. <hi>Item,</hi> That a Pacquet 10/20. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> arrived in <hi>London,</hi> from <hi>Thomas White</hi> Provincial, Mr. <hi>Stapleton,</hi> Mr, <hi>Nevil,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> Mr. <hi>Busby</hi> Procurator, and Maſter of the Humanity Schools, to <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> in which it was ſpecified that the Twelve Jeſuits were gone into <hi>Holland,</hi> and would uſe their skill and intereſt to make a Commotion there; and that the Apple-tree which the Deponent ſaith, is meant the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſhould not be Great, and they hoped the Fathers in <hi>London</hi> would follow their buſineſs cloſely, which Letters this Deponent ſaw and read.</p>
            <p n="57">57. That a Packet went from <hi>London</hi> 12/22 <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in which the Provincial was informed by <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> and the reſt, that the Court was gone, or going to <hi>Windſor,</hi> and the Fathers and honeſt <hi>William</hi> were ready to attend the Court, as this Deponent was informed by <hi>John Fenwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100713:15"/>
            <p n="58">58. That on <hi>August</hi> the 13. in the Afternoon, about Six of the Clock a Sermon was Preached by <hi>John Keines</hi> to Twelve Perſons, Men in poor habits (yet Men of Quality, as the Deponent ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believes) by the whiteneſs of their hands: In which Sermon, he did deliver that Proteſtants, and other Heretical Princes were depoſed <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> becauſe ſuch; and that it was as lawful to deſtroy them as <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> or any other Uſurper<hi>:</hi> At which Sermon the Deponent was preſent, not deſignedly, but by accident.</p>
            <p n="59">59. That on the 15/25 of <hi>Auguſt, John Keines,</hi> and <hi>John Fenwick</hi> went to a Gentlemans Lodging, in or about <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and perſwaded him to remove his Quarters, leaſt God deſtroyed him with the ſinners of the City, for God had raiſed them and others of their Society, to do ſuch things againſt the City, that would make a mans Eares to ring that ſhould hear it. The ſame Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Keines</hi> and <hi>Fenwick</hi> told the Deponent the Story, and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to think in what affright they had put the Gentleman into, whoſe name they named but cannot be called to mind by the Deponent.</p>
            <p n="60">60. <hi>Item,</hi> That <hi>John Keins</hi> came to the Lodging of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 17. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and told him it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to diſpatch 48. at <hi>Windſor,</hi> if poſſible, and withall told the Deponent that Mr. <hi>Howard</hi> Prior of the Benedictines, <hi>Hilch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock</hi> Sub-prior, and <hi>Skinner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cook,</hi> and ſome other Benedictines had promiſed to aſſiſt them with 6000 l. in order to the carrying on the deſign: Now the ſaid Monks did then by, at or near the <hi>Wardrobe</hi> behind the <hi>Savoy;</hi> which report the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> the Deponent did believe; for that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Howard</hi> Prior, and <hi>Hilchcock</hi> Sub-prior of the Benedictines, told the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent in the Morning, the 17. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> that they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſuch a Sum, and withall that the ſecuring his Majeſties Perſon, in flight from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> was the worſt days work that ever ſimple <hi>Jack Huddleſton</hi> did in all his life time, but now it was the time of their buſineſs, to get the Stewarts out of the way; which the Deponent related to <hi>John Keines,</hi> and he the ſaid <hi>John Keines</hi> did tell the Deponent, if he would undertake to aſſiſt in diſpatching the King, he ſhould be well rewarded, if not here, in Heaven; and the Deponent replyed, that he never ſhot off a Gun in all his life, and withall told the ſaid <hi>Keines,</hi> he could not be guilty of ſuch a thing for all the world: Then the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100713:15"/>
did further Inform the Deponent, that Mr. <hi>Coniers</hi> a Benedictine Monk, was reſolved to purſue the deſign of diſpatching 48. (which is the King) which appears to be evidently true to the Deponent; for he heard <hi>Coniers</hi> on the 14. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Lay a Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of One Hundred Pounds with a Gentleman (not known to the Deponent) in the Benedictine Covent, behind the <hi>Savoy,</hi> that the King ſhould not Live to Eat any more Chriſtmas Pyes, of which Wager Ten Guineys were by each party depoſited in the hands of Mr. <hi>Hilchcock</hi> Sub-Prior; ſo that the Deponent ſaid to <hi>Keines,</hi> he told him no more of <hi>Coniers</hi> than he heard from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the 14. <hi>Ditto.</hi> But the Deponent before he parted with <hi>Keines,</hi> asked him what News about the Town, and the ſaid <hi>Keine</hi> told the Deponent, that all the News was War with the <hi>French;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> did ſay, if that prove true, then have at the Rogues the Houſe of Commons, they ſhall be remembred for all their Long Bills againſt the Catholicks. The Deponent replyed, that with ſubmiſſion he thought that the revenge propoſed againſt them, would not do the buſineſs; and therefore not a reſolution conſiſtent with a Catholick Spirit; for the enterpriſe will be more Noble and Martial, and the Deponent urged he feared the death of the King would not ſcarcely do the buſineſs, and effect the deſign, unleſs His Royal Highneſs would pardon thoſe that did that Act, and ſtand by them in it. To which the ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> replyed, that the Duke was not the ſtrength of their truſt; for they had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to effect the ſetting up the Catholick Religion; for when they had diſpatched the King, they had a Liſt of Twenty Thouſand Catholicks in <hi>London,</hi> that were ſubſtantial Perſons, fit to bear Arms, that would Riſe in Twenty Four hours time and leſs; and if <hi>James</hi> would not comply with them to Plot, he muſt go alſo; it being late in the Night, The ſaid <hi>Keines</hi> prayed the Deponent to come to his Chamber at Eight of the Clock next Morning, and he would have an hours diſcourſe with him, before he ſaid Maſs; and being about to take his leave of the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, asked the Deponent what he meant by thoſe words, could not be guilty of ſuch a thing, as to aſſiſt in diſpatching the King, there being no guilt in the thing. The Deponent ſmiled, and ſaid, he would not be guilty of ſo much Courage: Beſides, the Deponent ſaith, that he told the ſaid <hi>Keines,</hi> that it was his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that it would be more ſafe to let Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi> try his skill, and then the People would not apprehend it ſo much.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100713:16"/>
            <p n="61">61. <hi>Item,</hi> That he went to <hi>Keines</hi> Chamber on the 18. in the Morning, about Eight or Nine of the Clock; but he was gone abroad, and left word that the Deponent ſhould come at Four in the Afternoon, and then he would have ſome Diſcourſe with him; and the Deponent went accordingly, but met Mr. <hi>Keines</hi> in the <hi>Mewſe,</hi> who ſaid he was to meet ſome of the Fathers in <hi>Covent Garden,</hi> and there would meet them ſome <hi>Dominicans;</hi> ſo would have the Deponent go along with them, and coming to the appointed houſe, the <hi>Dominicans</hi> were ready met, theſe <hi>(viz.)</hi> Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> Provincial of the Order of St. <hi>Dominick</hi> in <hi>England, Joſeph Davies, Kinmaſh,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dominick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Collins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fidding,</hi> Mr. <hi>Manſell</hi> and Mr. <hi>Launſdale,</hi> as they ſaid in the Name of all the reſt of the Order in <hi>England,</hi> to conſider and comply with the Fathers of the Society, to propagate the Catholick Faith, and when <hi>John Keines</hi> was ſat with the Fathers of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety by him (all on a ſide) <hi>John Keines,</hi> Father <hi>Hartcourt,</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Fenwick,</hi> Father <hi>Wright,</hi> and Father <hi>Blundel;</hi> the ſaid <hi>John Keines</hi> propounded to the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> to contribute to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of killing the King, and carrying on the buſineſs in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> The <hi>Dominicans</hi> anſwered by their Provincial, that they were Poor, and not able to do much; for they had but little or no money, but they would let them have their perſonal aſſiſtance and Councel, and procure what Intereſt they could; but as for money they could not part with any, for they were in Debt, and had ſcarce Four hundered pound in Stock, and the moſt they could make of their Eſtates, is Three hundered and ſixty pound <hi>per annum;</hi> at which Conſultation the Deponent was to and fro, and what was more ſaid, the Deponent cannot tell, for he was ſent with the Propoſals made to the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> to the <hi>Carmelites</hi> Doctor <hi>Hanſon,</hi> and <hi>Kemball,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Trevers,</hi> and they ſaid they had not One Penny in Stock, nor any Income, beſides the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſadors Allowance, for aſſiſting in his Chappel: They by the Deponent did preſent their Service to the Fathers met together, and bad him tell them their prayers to God and our Bleſſed Lady ſhould not be wanting: all which was acted by Order of the Provincial of the Society.</p>
            <p n="62">62. <hi>Item,</hi> the Deponent went to ſee <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> on the 19. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in the afternoon, and whilſt he was there, in comes <hi>John Keines,</hi> and preſently after him <hi>Richard Blundel,</hi> after Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation paſt they asked the Deponent what news, he anſwered he had heard none, but what was in the Gazett, then <hi>Blundel</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100713:16"/>
ſaid, he had been with his Work-men and they wanted Oyle (what the meaning of this is, the Deponent cannot poſitively tell,) but believes it was Sheeps Fat; for the ſaid <hi>Blundel,</hi> would not tell the Deponent his meaning by it, when asked<hi>:</hi> Then the Deponent asked of <hi>Keines</hi> when he was for <hi>Windor,</hi> he replied the Court was ſcarcely ſetled as yet, but ſaid, Mr. <hi>Coniers</hi> and Mr. <hi>Anderton</hi> were to go down on the Morrow, <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 20. and in the Morning. And if they did any thing as to the buſineſs in hand, it would haſten his going down, and therefore as yet could not certainly tell; when the Deponent asked further how honeſt <hi>William</hi> did, <hi>Keines</hi> replied he was troubled with a ſore Throat, and very bad with it, that he could not ride to <hi>Windſor,</hi> and it would be dangerous for him to go by Water, and that cold would be contracted, and he rendred unfit for ſervice. Then the Deponent took his leave of them, if being near Six of the Clock in the afternoon, and went to the <hi>Monks</hi> Convent, and enquired there of one <hi>Rumley</hi> a Lay Brother of the Orders, for Mr. <hi>Coniers,</hi> who ſaid he was not within, yet not far off, yet not to be ſpoken withal, for he was with ſome of the Benedictine Fathers about buſineſs, and on the Morrow Morning was to go out of Town betimes. So the Deponent left him, and being but a little way from the place met <hi>Coniers,</hi> who laughing, ſaid, the <note n="†" place="margin">Roone</note> 
               <hi>Still</hi> People were fools to ſet upon <note n="*" place="margin">The King</note> 48. at <hi>Windſor,</hi> becauſe he was ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in a poſture to receive their kindneſs, but he would ſee his Worſhip, and talk with him in ſome other Language. <note n="†" place="margin">Gun-powder.</note> Then <hi>Formillio,</hi> the Deponent asked him, how he replyed, that if the Shirt on his back knew he would Burn it; if that ſhould not take effect, no means or opportunity ſhould be neglected, in order to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of 48; he further told the Deponent he was in haſt, his time ſhort, and buſineſs great, but told the Deponent, honeſt <hi>William,</hi> and <hi>Pickering</hi> ſhould ſtay in Town, ſeeing the Perſon concerned was <hi>hic &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bique,</hi> never long in one place.</p>
            <p n="63">63. <hi>Item,</hi> That on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 21 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> a conſult was held by the Jeſuits then in <hi>London,</hi> with certain Benedictine Monks, about a Letter received from the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Dubline</hi> Talbot, to the Fathers of the Society, in which they were given to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that Four <hi>Iriſh</hi> Jeſuits, had undertaken the death of the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and upon his death the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were ready to riſe, and in his Letter told them, that a Legate was arrived in <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the <hi>Pope,</hi> and that he had aſſerted the <hi>Popes</hi> right
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100713:17"/>
to that Kingdom, and that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ceaſing from being <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, were no longer concerned therein, being given them during the good pleaſure of his Holineſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did incourage the ſaid Arch-Biſhop to contrive and uſe all means for the Recovery of that Kingdom out of the hands of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and in the ſaid Letter it was mentioned, that if oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities did not permit, the ſaid Jeſuits to do their buſineſs, that they ſhould ſend over one Dr. <hi>Foggarlie,</hi> now lodging at Mr. <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds,</hi> the Widow of <hi>Symmonds</hi> and Apothecary, and that he and the Fathers in <hi>Ireland,</hi> together with the ſaid <hi>Foggerlie,</hi> would find out an expedient way, for the death of the ſaid Duke of <hi>Ormond.</hi> Furthermore, he did ſpecifie, that they had procured ſeveral <hi>Iriſh</hi> to be made Commiſſioned Officers, in the Garriſons in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that he, and the reſt had diſpenced with them, to take the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy; and that the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that had ſo gotten Commiſſions by the Arch-biſhops means, had promiſed to betray their intereſt into their hands, when the buſineſs ſhould be ripe, and therefore deſired the Fathers to be diligent in <hi>England,</hi> as he and the reſt of the Clergy were in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which Letter <hi>John Keines</hi> did ſhew to, and read to this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, <hi>Keines</hi> and <hi>Blundel</hi> giving this Deponent an account of the conſultation, alſo <hi>Foggerlie</hi> did tell the ſame to the Deponent, on the 21. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and that he had great Intereſt in the Court of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="64">64. <hi>Item,</hi> That the ſaid <hi>Foggerly</hi> is a main Agent, in this Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Plot, and hath promiſed, if the Arch-biſhop <hi>Talbot</hi> will make uſe of him, he will do him all the Service he can, as the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent is ready to juſtifie, to the face of the ſaid <hi>Foggerlie,</hi> who did tell the Deponent, that himſelf and <hi>Coleman</hi> were in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, when <hi>Wakeman</hi> was contracted withal in order to Poyſon the King, and ſaid, if he had the intereſt in the King that <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had, he would have undertaken it himſelf, and all this was told the Deponent, on the 21 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in <hi>Foggerlies</hi> Chamber. And furthermore, the ſaid <hi>Foggerlie</hi> did then and there tell the Deponent, that he had hired Four <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ruſſians whoſe names he did neither tell the Conſulters that met that day nor the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, and they were to mind the Kings poſture at <hi>Windſor,</hi> but the Deponent telling the ſaid <hi>Foggerlie,</hi> he heard the King was gone to <hi>Porch-mouth,</hi> he was wonderfully troubled, by reaſon (as the ſaid <hi>Foggerlie</hi> did ſay) it did much impede their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and nothing would be attempted, as long as abſent from <hi>Windſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100713:17"/>
            <p n="65">65. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Lord Embaſſador at the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> Sir <hi>William Godalphin;</hi> holdeth great correſpondency, with <hi>Jerom Sinman</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Jeſuit before mentioned, Procurator for the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> alſo with the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Tuam</hi> now at <hi>Madrid,—</hi>as is a friend in his buſineſs, as the ſaid <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> did inform the Society in a Letter of the 30, of <hi>July,</hi> 1678 <hi>Stilo Novo.</hi> And likewiſe in one to the Deponent, wherein he did ſpecifie that Sir. <hi>William</hi> was as induſtrious as any one could be, to anſwer the expectations of the Society, and that he had one Proteſtant Servant and his Chapline in the Houſe <hi>(viz.)</hi> the the Cook which makes a couple, and the Deponent knows that <hi>Godolphin</hi> is a Papiſt, and has perverted a Kinſman of his own, alſo the Deponent knoweth the Embaſſador is very familiar with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Jeſuits, the Arch Biſhop <hi>Tuam</hi> and <hi>Sinman,</hi> and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent doth verily believe, that Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> ſometimes Chaplain to the Lord Embaſſador; if required teſtifie as much: and this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent further ſaith, that when he was at <hi>Madrid,</hi> the ſaid Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain has left his Employ, becauſe of the Embaſſadors being a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, and the Deponent hath ſeen the ſaid Embaſſador at Maſs, and hath a Jeſuit that comes to his Houſe, who reads both Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and Divinity to the ſaid Embaſſador, of which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent was perpetually informed by the ſaid <hi>Jerom Sinman,</hi> and the ſaid Arch-biſhop of <hi>Tuam</hi> both <hi>Iriſh</hi> Jeſuits of <hi>Madrid,</hi> but the Letters which the Deponent ſpeaks of, he ſaw and read at Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> houſe, <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 22 1678.</p>
            <p n="66">66. <hi>Item,</hi> That the 22 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Money was ſent from the Society by a Servant of theirs, to ſupply the expences of the Four Ruſſians mentioned, who were got to <hi>Windſor</hi> the 21. at Night, and the Sum ſent was 80 <hi>l.</hi> which the Deponent ſaw told, and they have written to, and informed them, that if more was wanting they ſhould have it, and they were bidden, not to be too frequent in one anothers Company, and always to profeſs but ſmall acquaintance, which order and Money was diſpatched away by <hi>Hartcourt</hi> Rector of <hi>London,</hi> in the Name of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial and whole Society.</p>
            <p n="67">67. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Deponent went to the Chamber of <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> which told him he was at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> with Ten or Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Students (as near as this Deponent remembers) there the, ſaid <hi>Fenwick</hi> was to attend the Provincial, and with him to return in Ten or Twelve days (as he ſaid) together with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100713:18"/>
               <hi>Micho</hi> and others. And while the Deponent was with the ſaid <hi>Fenwick,</hi> a Meſſenger came in <hi>(viz.) John Groves,</hi> with Orders from <hi>Hartcourt</hi> Rector of <hi>London, John Keines, Richard Blundel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Write, Bazill Long worth,</hi> and Four other Jeſuits that lie at <hi>Sommerſet-houſe,</hi> to pray the Provincial to write to <hi>Leſhee</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Kings Confeſſor, and let him know how well the buſineſs in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſtood, and deſire him to acquaint the <hi>French</hi> King therewith; the Deponent asked <hi>Groves,</hi> where the Fathers were met again at Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> houſe, and the Deponent after he had received the Orders or Memorial, for ſo it was Inſtituted, and ſaw their Names about Two of the Clock in the Afternoon, he went to the houſe of Mr. <hi>Saundirs,</hi> where this Deponent ſaw theſe Fathers, who told them of the ſaid Order, and after a ſhort ſtay took his leave of them, and by them was Ordered to meet them at Four of the Clock at Mr. <hi>Keines</hi> Chamber, where the Deponent met them, where he ſaw Doctor <hi>Foggarlie,</hi> who ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a Letter Writ to Mr. <hi>Benning field</hi> with his own hand, and likewiſe the Deponent ſaw Letters from <hi>Blundel</hi> and <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> and one from Father <hi>Ireland</hi> at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> but that of Dr. <hi>Foggarlies</hi> to Mr. <hi>Benning field</hi> did contain in it, an account of Eight Letters that were written to the Jeſuits, ſome of which were delivered to the Poſt Office in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet,</hi> others to the General Poſt Office, others ſent by Private Meſſengers to Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> a Jeſuit, who lived with Mr. <hi>Charles Shelly</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> that Married the Relict of the Baron of <hi>Abergamy,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Peters</hi> was Orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to meet with the Provincial at <hi>London,</hi> about the deſign in hand, which if it take not effect at <hi>Windſor,</hi> then ſpeedily <hi>John Keines</hi> was to go to <hi>Windſor,</hi> to meet with <hi>Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> who was deſigned to go out of Town, on the 20. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant with Mr. <hi>Anderton</hi> to <hi>Windſor,</hi> 440. and after their buſineſs was done at <hi>Keines</hi> Chamber, the Deponent left them.</p>
            <p n="68">68. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Deponent being to meet Doctor <hi>Tongue,</hi> on the 22. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-head</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inn-Lane,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Six of the Clock at Night; accordingly he went, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctor was not come, he walked into the Walks, and there he met with <hi>Coniers,</hi> who was ſuppoſed to be gone to <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor:</hi> The Deponent asked how it happened he went not his Journey; he told him his Horſe fell ſo Lame, he could ſcarce carry him Three Miles on the way; and he himſelf was troubled with the <hi>Sciatica,</hi> which had given him great trouble all the Night before. The Deponent was then urgent with him to tell
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100713:18"/>
him how he would kill the King, ſeeing he laughed at the Means the Fathers intended to uſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by ſhooting him; then ſaid <hi>Coniers</hi> by reaſon of the Deponents Importunity (ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a Dagger, or a Knife Two edged) with a very ſharp point, and broad towards the Haft, which was of <hi>Bucks-horn,</hi> being a Foot long in the Blade, and near half a Foot in the Haft; with this ſaid he, ſhall the Villain fall to the Ground, if it be poſſible. <hi>Coniers</hi> demanded of the Deponent what he thought it might Coſt, the Deponent anſwered, he could not tell. He replyed Ten Shillings or there about; the Deponent ſaid it was too dear, and he ſaid nothing could be too dear for the King; the Deponent asked him where he bought it: <hi>Coniers</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed at the Old <hi>Cutlers</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet;</hi> the Deponent asked him why he made it ſo long; he replyed that the Villain might fall by it; the Deponent asked him how he ſaid through his Cloak—The Deponent asked him how he could hope to eſcape. <hi>Coniers</hi> anſwered, he doubted not but to obtain a Pardon, if he were not knockt in the head on the ſame place; the Deponent after ſome ſhort diſcourſe, went to the <hi>Kings-head,</hi> where he met Doctor <hi>Tongue</hi> between Six and Seven of the Clock at Night.</p>
            <p n="69">69. That the Deponent did on the ſame 22. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> about Nine at Night meet Mr. <hi>Blundel,</hi> and ſeeing him have a Bag, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him what he had; he replyed <hi>Tukesbury Muſtard-balls,</hi> a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and biting Sauce, and would furniſh <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> when he had enough of them.</p>
            <p n="70">70. <hi>Item,</hi> That on the 24. of <hi>Auguſt, Blundel</hi> told the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in <hi>Fenwicks</hi> Chamber, that it would be ſo ordered by the Society, that the Catholicks of <hi>England</hi> would endeavour to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the deſign in hand, for ſhortning the Kings days, and bid the Deponent be of good Courage, for Proteſtant Religion was now on its laſt Legs.</p>
            <p n="71">71. <hi>Item,</hi> That on the Thirtieth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Deponent met with the ſaid <hi>Blundel;</hi> who told him he muſt ſhew him what <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and the Houſes on both ſides the Water muſt be done withal, and carried the Deponent to <hi>Fenwicks</hi> Chamber, and there drew out a Letter-Caſe and Paper, in which the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Firing <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and the Houſes on both ſides the Water muſt be done withal, and carried the Deponent to <hi>Fenwicks</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>Wapping, Tooly-ſtreet, Barnaby-ſtreet,</hi> and St. <hi>Thomas</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were contained. Firſt, for <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> if the Wind was
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100713:19"/>
Northerly, then they were to begin at the next door to the <hi>Pauls-graves-head</hi> Tavern; the Jeſuits and their Agents were to carry it on to the <hi>Savoy,</hi> then the Benedictines were to carry it down on both ſides to <hi>Charing-Croſs,</hi> then the Jeſuits and other Agents to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and were to the end of the <hi>Stone-Gallery;</hi> another Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to begin and carry it into <hi>King-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Channel-Row,</hi> which was firſt to be Acted in the great Fire 1666. But then they were not aſſured of the <hi>French</hi> Kings aſſiſtance, which they are now aſſured by <hi>Leſhee</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Kings Confeſſor (as the ſaid <hi>Blundel</hi> told the Deponent) at the ſame time <hi>Wapping,</hi> and the Ships in the <hi>River</hi> were to be burned; and in Caſe the Wind blew up the <hi>River,</hi> the Fire to begin at a Place near <hi>Bugbies-hole;</hi> and is to be carryed on by Four men, they have made ſure of <hi>Wapping</hi> Middle-ſtairs; and then Four or Five more to carry it up higher. The Deponent himſelf with Seven more, were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to ply about the <hi>Hermitage;</hi> and his buſineſs was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Seven committed to his Care, and for his reward, One thouſand pound was promiſed, beſides Eighty pound for former ſervice; but the Deponent ſaith, in that Paper was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained if the Wind ſtood contrary, they ſhould change the Fire; at the ſame time others were to have the charge of <hi>Tooly-ſtreet, Barnaby,</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtles on the other ſide the Water committed to them, and the Fire is to begin on <hi>Redriff</hi> ſide, when it begins at <hi>Wapping,</hi> or preſently after: And this is to be done when the Tides are low, that the Ships get not off from the Keys, in order to the Deponents managing that part of the Fire committed to his own care at the <hi>Hermitage;</hi> he was orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to remove his Lodging into <hi>Wapping</hi> as ſoon as Orders ſhould be given him, and ſhould have a Prieſt come to him, and ſay Maſs in his Chamber for good ſucceſs to the deſign; but the Deponent ſaith, he did not know he was to be an Agent in the buſineſs, till he ſaw the Paper was ſigned by <hi>Thomas White</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, in the name of the whole Society.</p>
            <p n="72">72. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Deponent ſaith, that the Pope hath Iſſued a Bull, a Coppy of which Mr. <hi>Blundel</hi> ſhewed this Deponent on the 30. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and as near as he remembers, bares Date, <hi>November</hi> or <hi>December</hi> laſt; in which the Pope was pleaſed to Order, and diſpoſe of the Biſhopricks in <hi>England,</hi> and other Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the ſame, as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100713:19"/>
            <list>
               <head>ARCH-BISHOPS.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Howard,</hi> with an Addition of Forty thouſand Crowns <hi>per annum,</hi> for maintaining of a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatine Power and Authority.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Yorke, Perrot</hi> ſuperior to the ſecular Prieſts, who hath Power of Probate of Wills, Licences for Marriages, and all Epiſcopal Juriſdiction, except Ordination and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>BISHOPS.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>London, Corker</hi> Preſident of the Benedictines.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Winchester, White</hi> Provincial of the Jeſuits.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Durham, Strange</hi> Late Provincial of the Jeſuits.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Doctor <hi>Godden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Norwich, Napper</hi> a Franciſcan Fryer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ely, Vincent</hi> Provincial of the Dominicans.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Exeter, Wolfe</hi> one of the Sherbon.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peterborow, Gifford</hi> a Dominican.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lincoln,</hi> Sir <hi>John Warner</hi> Barronet, a Jeſuit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chicheſter, Morgan</hi> a Jeſuit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bath and Wells,</hi> Doctor <hi>Armſtrong</hi> a Franciſcan Fryer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Carlile, Wilmot</hi> a ſecular Prieſt, <hi>alias</hi> Quartermain.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cheſter, Thimbleby</hi> a ſecular new Cannon of <hi>Cambray.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hereford,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Preſton</hi> Jeſuit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Briſtoll, Mounſon</hi> a Dominican.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oxford, Williams</hi> Rector of <hi>Watton,</hi> and Maſter of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices: he is to have the Denary of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and is to have Precedence over Profeſſors in Divinity, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe their Lectures ere they read them in Publick.</item>
               <item>St. <hi>Davids,</hi> a ſecular Prieſt <hi>Benſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>St. <hi>Aſaph, Jones</hi> a ſecular.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bangor, Joſeph Davis, Kinmaſh</hi> a Dominican.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>ABBOTS.</head>
               <item>Of <hi>Westminſter,</hi> Doctor <hi>Sheldon</hi> a Benedictine Monk.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Sion houſe, Skinner</hi> a Benedictine.</item>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100713:20"/>
               <item>Of <hi>Canterbury, Bettum</hi> a Sorboniſt.</item>
               <item>Of St. <hi>Pauls, Leyborn,</hi> a Secular, and Secretary to the Cardinal.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Windſor, Howard</hi> with Twelve Benedictine Cannons.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Chicheſter, Morgan</hi> a ſecular.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> Doctor <hi>Watkinſon</hi> Preſident of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colledge at <hi>Lisbourn;</hi> many Dignities of the Church not here named, are to be ſupplied by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and other Forreigners; becauſe they have not Clergy enough to be Profeſſors, nor are there any Prebendaries, or other Places undiſpoſed; and in the ſame Bull it was ordered that the Jeſuits read Philoſophy and Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in all great Towns, and Places where they had Colledges, but not give Degrees; and whilſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Jeſuits are imployed in Inſtructing in Humanity and Philoſophy, and others in reading Divinity, Preaching and Catechizing, they ſhould be ſupplyed by <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Jeſuits, and other Forreigners to aſſiſt at the Altar, and in the care of the Colledges.</p>
            <p n="73">73. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Deponent ſaw the Second of <hi>September,</hi> a Pacquet out of <hi>Scotland</hi> directed to <hi>John Groves,</hi> Dated <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 20. 1678. in which the Fathers from thence met at <hi>Edenbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi> did tell the Fathers here, that they had not much to write, but that Eighty thouſand Catholicks in that Kingdom were ready to Riſe and aſſiſt when the buſineſs ſhould grow hot, and would joyn with the diſaffected <hi>Scots</hi> when required by the <hi>Scotch</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits; and in the ſaid Letter it was mentioned that one <hi>Weſtby</hi> was deſtroyed, by one that was Servant to one <hi>Lovel</hi> a Jeſuit, for endeavouring to detect the Rebellion, with its Authors and Contrivers to the Council of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="74">74. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Deponent ſaw on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>/12 <hi>September,</hi> Letters of the Fourth, <hi>Stilo Novo,</hi> from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> written and ſubſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by <hi>Thomas Whitebread</hi> Provincial, in which was given to <hi>Blundel,</hi> to whom the Letter was directed; that Twelve <hi>Scotch</hi> Jeſuits were ſent into <hi>Scotland,</hi> by Order from the General of the Society, and have One thouſand pound given them by <hi>Leſhee</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Kings Confeſſor, to keep up the Commotion in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> King may Land an Army in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that the ſaid Jeſuits, had Orders to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like Non-Conformiſt Miniſters amongſt the Presbyterian <hi>Scots.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:100713:20"/>
            <p n="75">75. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Third of <hi>September,</hi> this Deponent ſaw a Letter from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> from the Provincial; but it was Dated the Firſt of <hi>September,</hi> by which the Deponent did perceive that though the Letter was Dated from thence, it came not from thence, becauſe it was <hi>Old Stile,</hi> and thereby did believe the Provincial was in <hi>England.</hi> Fifteenth, a Letter directed to <hi>Blundel,</hi> was ſpecified that the Provincial was informed of ſome diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries made; at which he was ſomewhat ſurpriſed, and upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts Ordered the ſaid <hi>Blundel</hi> to deſiſt the buſineſs in hand; but to write to <hi>Benningfield</hi> not to take notice what <hi>Keines</hi> ſaid, it being but a conceit of his own, and the ſaid <hi>Blundel</hi> did on the Third of <hi>September</hi> write to <hi>Benningfield,</hi> and did adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe him of the Provincials thoughts, concerning what had paſt about that concern; and in the Letter of the Provincial to <hi>Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del,</hi> it was ordered that thanks ſhould be given to Doctor <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly,</hi> for his Care in the buſineſs of 48. (the King) and for his forwardneſs to aſſiſt thoſe in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Ordered Letters to be ſent thither with all ſpeed, and give them his thanks, and tell him he would not ceaſe to pray for their good ſucceſs.</p>
            <p n="76">76. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Provincial came to <hi>London</hi> on the Third day at Night, and the Deponent went to his Lodging, and was ordered to wait upon him next Morning.</p>
            <p n="77">77. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Deponent went on the Fourth in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, according to the aforeſaid Orders, and when the Provincial ſaw the Deponent; he asked him with what face he could look on him, ſince that he the Deponent had plaid him ſuch a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous trick, and ſtrook him Three Blows with his Stick, and a Box on the Ear, and charged him with being with the King, and a Miniſter with him; whom he ſuſpected to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the King of theſe things; becauſe that <hi>Benningfield</hi> had related in a Letter to <hi>Blundel,</hi> that the Duke of <hi>York</hi> had ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted ſome ſuch thing to him, and did therefore Judge that it muſt be ſo by the Deponent, that muſt have been drawn in by ſome perſon to the ſame; but at laſt the Provincial told the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent he was willing to be reconciled to him, if he would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover who the perſon was, his Name, and place of abode; to the end he might be ſecured of him; and were reſolved to kill him, and in the mean time the Deponent was ordered to make himſelf ready to go Beyond-Sea within Fourteen days (as the Provincial ſaid) and that the Deponent might not cheat them,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100713:21"/>
they were to pay for his Coach-hire, and ordered him entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Sittingborne,</hi> and other places on the Road to <hi>Dover;</hi> and there Mr. <hi>Coniers</hi> at the <hi>Kings-head</hi> was to pay for his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> where the ſaid Deponent was to remain till further Orders from the Provincial, and <hi>R. Blundel</hi> was to take care of carrying on the Fire at <hi>Wapping,</hi> in the Deponents Room.</p>
            <p n="78">78. <hi>Item,</hi> on the Sixth of <hi>September, Pickering</hi> told the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent that <hi>Coniers</hi> was gone to <hi>Windſor,</hi> and he ſaid after Ten days ſtay, he would go to the Lord <hi>Brudnels</hi> Houſe.</p>
            <p n="79">79. <hi>Item,</hi> That about Night the Deponent attending the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincials door, and about to go in, he heard <hi>White</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom the Deponent ſuppoſes by their Voices to be Father <hi>Micho,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Pool,</hi> conſulting about the diſpoſing a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he ſuppoſes to be himſelf, their words were theſe; this man has betrayed us, and therefore we will give a Coach-man Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pound, to take him up and carry him directly to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> to Eſquire <hi>Leeds</hi> houſe who lives near the Town, and from thence to <hi>Dover</hi> by ſome by way, becauſe he was acquainted at <hi>Sitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn,</hi> and ſaid if they could get him beyond-ſea, they would tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him till he had confeſſed to them, who it was that had been with the King, and informed him of the buſineſs, when the Deponent heard theſe words he made haſt away and durſt not lie that night in his own Lodgings.</p>
            <p n="80">80. <hi>Item,</hi> That the Seventh of <hi>September</hi> at Night, the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent returned to his Lodgings, where he intended not to lye, but only to take ſome neceſſaries for his uſe the next day; but meeting one <hi>Grigson</hi> a Papiſt, at whoſe houſe he had formerly lodged near the <hi>Read-Lion</hi> in <hi>Drury-lane;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Grigson</hi> told him that the Jeſuits were diſpleaſed with him, becauſe he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered not their expectations, in being true to them, and that the Jeſuits are dangerous perſons, and would ruin him if they could; and ſaid further, that the ſaid <hi>Grigson</hi> had known their Rogeries this Twelve or Fourteen years; and the Deponent being through diſcourſe detained by him, was forced to lye in his Lodging in <hi>Drury-Lane;</hi> and when the Deponent was laid down in his Bed, one <hi>Stratford</hi> (a perſon utterly unknown to the Deponent, diſcourſed with, or any otherwiſe provoked) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to break into the houſe, where the Deponent lay, and broke down a door to get into his Lodging, but was forced
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100713:21"/>
back, becauſe he apprehended himſelf to be obſerved by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; and when he ſaw he could not come at him to Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate him (as he verily believes); he reviled him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Deponent, and brake ſeveral Quarrels of Glaſs in a Window under his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the Deponent being therefore verily perſwaded, that <hi>Strat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> was ſet on by the Jeſuits, to do him a miſchief, made his eſcape thence eaſily on <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning; but durſt not return thither again, becauſe that <hi>Stratford</hi> threatned to kill him; now the Houſe where the Deponent lay is a School, where <hi>Blundel</hi> uſually Catechized every <hi>Sunday</hi> in the Afternoon.</p>
            <p n="81">81. <hi>Item, September</hi> the Eighth, whilſt this Deponent was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to attend Gods worſhip in the City of <hi>London,</hi> a Papiſt, who goes by the Name of <hi>Nevil,</hi> met him in the <hi>Strand,</hi> and told the Deponent there was great murmuring amongſt the Jeſuits againſt him; becauſe a complaint was made againſt them by ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of whom he was ſuſpected one. The ſaid <hi>Nevil</hi> did tell the Deponent that it was reported he muſt ruin the Jeſuits, or they him; telling him moreover, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> was made acquainted with it, and ſaid he would lead them ſuch a Dance, as they never followed ſince the Fool their Founder came into the World; to which this Deponent made no reply, but taking this perſon to be a Trapan, when asked for his Lodging, gave no account.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The Names of the Conſpirators, and where they are.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Jeſuits.</head>
               <item>THomas White <hi>Provincial</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Richard Strange, <hi>late Provincial</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Richard Aſhbey <hi>alias</hi> Thimbleby, England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Hartcourt</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Jeniſon <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>John Keines <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>William Wright <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Richard Blundel <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Gregory Pool <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Micho <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Benningfield <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Langworth <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Morgan <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100713:22"/>
               <item>Richard Peters <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Dorrington <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Lacy <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Vaughan <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Every <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Preſton <hi>at</hi> Leige.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> John Warner <hi>at</hi> Watton.</item>
               <item>Thomas Stapleton <hi>at St.</hi> Omers.</item>
               <item>Thomas Farmor <hi>at St.</hi> Omers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Eggleſtone <hi>at</hi> Watton.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Sanders <hi>at</hi> Leige.</item>
               <item>Edward Hull <hi>at St.</hi> Omers.</item>
               <item>Coniers <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Launell <hi>and</hi> Chriſtopher Peters <hi>at St.</hi> Omers.</item>
               <item>Jeniſon <hi>at</hi> Watton.</item>
               <item>Marſh <hi>at</hi> Ghent.</item>
               <item>John Peters <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Blake <hi>alias</hi> Croſs <hi>in</hi> Spain.</item>
               <item>Munford <hi>in</hi> Spain.</item>
               <item>Wilkinſon <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Woolfe <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Nevel <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Sabrand <hi>at St.</hi> Omers.</item>
               <item>Walker <hi>at St.</hi> Omers.</item>
               <item>Roper <hi>at St.</hi> Omers.</item>
               <item>Conſtable <hi>at St.</hi> Omers.</item>
               <item>Canny <hi>at</hi> Rome.</item>
               <item>Crane <hi>at</hi> Watton.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Benedictines.</head>
               <item>Howard <hi>at</hi> Doway.</item>
               <item>Hilchcock <hi>at</hi> Doway.</item>
               <item>Anderton <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Coniers <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Rumly <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100713:22"/>
               <item>Cocker <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Skinner <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Crosby <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Reeves <hi>at</hi> Doway.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Carmelites.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Hanſon <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Trevers <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Kemball <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Franciſcans.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Napper <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Armſtrong <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Dominicans.</head>
               <item>Joſeph David Kinmaſh <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Dominick <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Collins <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Vincent <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Hidden <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Manſell <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Lynſdale <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Captain</hi> Busby <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Cooper <hi>at</hi> Rome.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Secular Prieſts.</head>
               <item>Perrot <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Morgan <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Willmot <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Godden <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Jones <hi>Senior in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Jones <hi>Junior in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Woolfe <hi>in</hi> France.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Theſe Seven only by Information.</head>
               <item>Gerrard <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Herick <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Fiſher <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Jackson <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kerd <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>Sharpe <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Preſton <hi>in</hi> England.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100713:23"/>
            <list>
               <head>Scotch Jeſuits.</head>
               <item>Lovell</item>
               <item>Saunders</item>
               <item>More</item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Twelve <hi>Jeſuits</hi> whoſe Names I know not, lately gone into <hi>Scotland,</hi> but their Perſons I know.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>Secular perſons.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Foggerly</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> George Wakeman</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Coleman</item>
                  <item>John Groves.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Aſſaſſinates.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Four</hi> Iriſh.</item>
                  <item>Pickering <hi>Lay-Brothers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Smith <hi>Lay-Brothers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Talbot <hi>and</hi> Lynn Arch-Biſhops.</item>
                  <item>Jerom Sinman.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Godolphin,</hi> Lord Embaſſador in <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>
               <hi>The Examination of</hi> Titus Oates <hi>before the</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</head>
            <p>WHo begins his Account from King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, and tells them that he and His Son Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> were both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched out of this World before their times, by what means, and by whom, he gave an account how the laſt Rebellion begun, and what the Jeſuits were, concerned in the death of the Late King; how they Fired the City in 66. what Perſons managed every ſtreet; what Ingredients the Fire-works were made of, and where they were made; he further giveth an Account of the Firing St. <hi>Katharines,</hi> and <hi>Southwark,</hi> and that lately at <hi>Limehouſe</hi> and ſeveral other places in the Country, he acquaints them that the Rector of St. <hi>Omers</hi> gives the <hi>French</hi> King an account of the Tranſactions here, and relates theſe Correſpondencies in Town; he tells this Conſpiracy hath been hatching ever ſince King <hi>James</hi>'s
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100713:23"/>
time, only the Meaſures and Inſtruments have been altered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeveral ages; he names the Jeſuits that are in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> under the Character of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters, to Preach up Rebellion there; he ſaith that the <hi>French</hi> King hath already Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> being thoſe Forces that left <hi>Meſſina,</hi> and it is to make them up 25000. which are to joyn with the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> in a ſecond Maſſacre, to Fire the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and deſtroy the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> and his Adherents, and that part of the Conſpiracy was managed by <hi>Coleman,</hi> and that the King was to be killed by Three perſons whom he named; any of them to take an Opportunity, and uſe all means they thought moſt effectual, that there was a Fire to be begun without <hi>Temple-bar,</hi> and to be carried on to <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> ſeveral Porters being aſſigned to manage it; he ſaith the Cyphers uſed for the Kings Name in all their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viates was 48. for the Nation 66. for the Parliament they called them <hi>Barly-broth,</hi> he tells them there was ſuch and ſuch Jeſuits in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to ſtir up Animoſities among the people, and to ſet them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>
               <hi>The Examination of</hi> Titus Oates <hi>before the</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice, <hi>October</hi> 24 1678.</head>
            <p>This Examinant ſaith, that in the Moneth of <hi>May</hi> laſt, he ſaw a Patent under the Seal of the Father General of the Society of Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at <hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Johannis Paulus de Oliva,</hi> at the Chamber of Mr. <hi>Langhorn;</hi> wherein it was expreſſed that by vertue of a <hi>Breviat</hi> from the <hi>Pope,</hi> he did conſtitute the Lord <hi>Arundel of Warder,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> which Patent was ſent to the Lord <hi>Arundel of Warder,</hi> by a Meſſenger who was the Son of Mr. <hi>Langhorn,</hi> and this Examinant ſaith, that he ſaw a Letter ſubſcribed by the Lord <hi>Arundel of Warder</hi> as he believed; wherein he acknowledged the receipt of the ſame Patent, and accepted of the ſame, and promiſed to ask acceptation of the Society.</p>
            <p>This Examinant ſaith, that in <hi>June</hi> laſt he ſaw the Patent, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my Lord <hi>Powis</hi> was Conſtituted Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> which Patent was carried by one Parſons Secretary to the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> from one <hi>Sanders</hi>'s houſe in <hi>Wildſtreet,</hi> to be delivered to the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> and at the delivery of the Patent 300 <hi>l.</hi> was paid by Parſons to one <hi>Fenwick</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to carry on the deſign of the Jeſuits, which was to raſe Rebellion in the Three Kingdoms, and deſtroy the King. In the Month of <hi>July,</hi> this Examinant ſaw a Letter ſubſcribed <hi>Powis,</hi> directed to <hi>Fenwick;</hi> wherein his Lordſhip did own the receipt of the ſaid Patent, and did accept of the ſame, and ſaid he had 300. Men
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100713:24"/>
and Horſe ready for the deſign, and that he would venture his life and fortune for the Affair.</p>
            <p>In the Month of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, This Examinant ſaw a Letter dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to Mr. <hi>Langhorn</hi> by the outſide, but within to the Society of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, wherein Sir. <hi>William Godolphin</hi> acknowledged, he had receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the like patent to be Lord Privy Seal, and he accepted thereof, and in <hi>July</hi> 1677. This Examinant ſaw the ſame Patent in the hands of the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Evan</hi> at <hi>Madrid</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Examinant ſaith in <hi>July</hi> laſt Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> acknowledged, and confeſſed to <hi>John Fenwick,</hi> in this Examinants preſence, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the like Commiſſion or Patent to be Secretary of State, this was a good exchange.</p>
            <p>This Examinant ſaith, that in <hi>May, June, July</hi> and <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, this Examinant ſaw Two Letters Signed <hi>Stafford,</hi> whereby it did appear that my Lord <hi>Stafford</hi> was in the Conſpiracy againſt His Majeſty, and that he had returned ſeveral Summs of Mony to the Jeſuits to carry on the deſign, theſe Letters were directed to <hi>Fenwick</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> this Examinant ſaw another Letter directed to the ſame perſons, ſigned <hi>Stafford,</hi> wherein my Lord writ, that although he hath ſent his ſon to <hi>Lisbone,</hi> yet he would be never the worſe friends to the Jeſuits, and this Examinant conceives the reaſon of that Letter, was becauſe there was a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colledge at <hi>Liſbone</hi> and the Jeſuits.</p>
            <p>In <hi>July</hi> laſt, this Examinant ſaw in the hands of <hi>Fenwick</hi> a Commiſſion, directed to my Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> from the perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid to be General of the Army, to be raiſed in <hi>England</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Majeſty, and in the ſame Month this Examinant ſaw a Letter directed from my Lord to <hi>Fenwick,</hi> wherein his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip acknowledged the receipt thereof, and thanked the Society for the ſame, and he accepted of and would do what in him lay, to anſwer their exſpectation; in <hi>May</hi> laſt, this Examinant ſaw a patent in the hand of Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi> to make the Lord <hi>Peters</hi> Lievtenant General of the Army; and in <hi>June</hi> laſt, this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant did hear my Lord <hi>Peters,</hi> in the preſence of Mr. <hi>Langworth</hi> his Confeſſor, acknowledge the receipt of the ſame, and that he accepted thereof, and his Confeſſor preſently wiſhed him much joy thereof.</p>
            <p>This Examinant in <hi>July</hi> laſt at the <hi>Pheſant</hi> in <hi>Fullers-rents,</hi> on a <hi>Sunday</hi> did give one <hi>Penny</hi> a Commiſſion to be a Captain of Foot, this <hi>Pennys</hi> Siſter is Servant to the Queen as <hi>Penny</hi> ſaid, the like
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100713:24"/>
Commiſſion for Mr. <hi>John Carrol</hi> to be a Captain of Horſe, at my Lady <hi>Dramants</hi> in <hi>July</hi> laſt, and gave the Examinant Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Shillings, that is to ſay Four new Crowns.</p>
            <p>This Examinant ſaith, he delivered a Commiſſion to one Mr. <hi>Townly,</hi> at the <hi>Red-Poſts</hi> in <hi>Wildſtreet</hi> to be Captain of Foot, this was delivered in <hi>July</hi> or <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Examinant ſaith that in <hi>July</hi> laſt, he ſaw Mr. <hi>Fenwick</hi> fill a blank Commiſſion, which he informed this Examinant, was a Commiſſion to Sir. <hi>George Wakeman</hi> to be Phyſician to the Army, and this Examinant ſaith, that he knoweth that Sir <hi>George Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> is Phyſician to the Society of Jeſuits, and hath ſeen his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
            <p>This Examinant ſaith that in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, there was a Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at which Sir <hi>George Wakeman, William Herrent, John Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, Nicholas Blundel, John Keines, Thomas Jeniſon, Edward Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Foggarly</hi> was preſent, and that 15000 <hi>l.</hi> was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi> to Poyſon the King, who accepted thereof, and then received of <hi>Coleman</hi> 5000 <hi>l.</hi> in part, this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant not being well, was not preſent at that Conſultation, but was informed of it by <hi>Foggarly, Fenwick,</hi> and <hi>Blundel,</hi> and this Examinant ſaw the Levy thereof, with <hi>Fenwicks</hi> hand, and <hi>Foggarlie</hi> told this Examinant, that he told Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi> if he had ſuch Intereſt at Court as <hi>Wakeman</hi> had, that he would have undertaken it himſelf, and ſo he told this Examinant that he would have done it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sworn before me (by <hi>Titus Oates) William Scrogs,</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>This following Examination taken upon Oath before us, Sir <hi>Edmund Windham,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Stringer,</hi> and Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS to the circumſtance of time and place, this Examinant ſaith he cannot certainly depoſe as to ſuch particulars, but ſaith, in the Moneths of <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July</hi> laſt, this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent did in <hi>Wild-garden,</hi> deliver to Sir <hi>Francis Ratcliff</hi> Baronet, a Commiſſion to be Major General of the Army, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Eldeſt Son, who at the ſame time received from this Examinant a Commiſſion, to be Captain in the ſaid Army, and at the delivering of the ſaid Commiſſion, Sir <hi>Francis</hi> Orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Son to give this Examinant Three Ginneys, which he did accordingly, this Examinant never ſaw Sir <hi>Francis Ratcliff</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100713:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then, other then his Son, who he was very well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, who told this Examinant that Sir <hi>Franois</hi> was his Father.</p>
            <p>This Examinant ſaith that in <hi>June</hi> laſt, he ſaw in the hands of <hi>Fenwick,</hi> a Commiſſion or Patent to <hi>John Lambert,</hi> to be Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutant General to the Army, and in <hi>July</hi> after, this Examinant ſaw a Letter directed to <hi>Fenwick,</hi> wherein <hi>Lambert</hi> confeſſed the receipt of the ſaid Commiſſion, and accepted of the ſame, and this Examinant is well acquainted with <hi>Lamberts Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Examinant ſaw Mr. <hi>Langhorn</hi> to have a Commiſſion to be Advocate General in his Own hands, in <hi>May</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p>This Examinant in <hi>May</hi> laſt, ſaw a Commiſſion to the Eldeſt Son of the Lord <hi>Arundell of Warder,</hi> to be Commiſſion General of the Army, and heard he accepted of the ſame, at the ſame time his Father received it.</p>
            <p>This Examinant in <hi>June</hi> laſt, ſaw a Commiſſion in the hands of <hi>Fenwick</hi> to my Lord <hi>Baltimore,</hi> to be Colonel of Horſe in the Army, and <hi>Fenwick</hi> delivered it to <hi>Groves,</hi> and this Examinant went with <hi>Groves</hi> to my Lord <hi>Baltimores</hi> door, and <hi>Grove</hi> carried the Commiſſion into the houſe, and told the Examinant he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it to my Lord, and this Examinant within Two or Three days after ſaw a Letter from my Lord, wherein he acknowledged the receipt of it.</p>
            <p>There was a Commiſſion to Colonel <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> delivered him by this Examinant to be Colonel in the Army (but he is ſince dead) this was delivered in <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July</hi> laſt in <hi>Wild Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Examinant in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, delivered a Commiſſion to Mr. <hi>Leſhley,</hi> to be a Colonel of Horſe in the Army, to be raiſed againſt His Maieſty, this was delivered in a houſe in the <hi>Strand</hi> near the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and this <hi>Leſhley</hi> gave this Examinant a Ginney the ſame time.</p>
            <p>Another Commiſſion delivered in the ſame Moneth to one <hi>Roper,</hi> to be a Colonel by this Examinant, and another to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> Son to be a Captain, and the Father gave this Examinant Ten ſhillings.</p>
            <p>In <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July</hi> laſt, he delivered on to <hi>Matthew Medborn</hi> to be a Captain, this was delivered at his houſe in <hi>Plough-yard</hi> in <hi>Fetter-lane,</hi> and at the ſame time, he gave his Examinant a Black Hat for a White one.</p>
            <p>This Examinant in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, delivered a Commiſſion to one <hi>Winter</hi> or <hi>Wittor</hi> to be a Colonel of Foot.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100713:25"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
